<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The practices of persecutors delivered in a sermon on the fourteenth verse of the foure score six Psalme / b Mr. Archibald Skeldie.</title>
            <author>Skeldie, Archibald.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60325</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3932</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20904</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12294673</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12294673</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58988</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60325)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58988)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 160:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The practices of persecutors delivered in a sermon on the fourteenth verse of the foure score six Psalme / b Mr. Archibald Skeldie.</title>
                  <author>Skeldie, Archibald.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 57 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by James Lindesay ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXXXVI, 14 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Persecution.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58988:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58988:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PRACTICES OF PERSECVTORS: Delivered in a Sermon on the fourteenth Verſe <hi>of the foure-ſcore ſix PSALME.</hi> BY M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>ARCHIBALD SKELDIE.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>The wicked in his pride doth perſecute the poore.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalme</hi> 10. verſe 1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>They have ſaid, Come, and let us cut them off from beeing a Nation: that the name of Iſrael may be no more in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalme</hi> 83.4.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Auguſt. in Pſal. 39.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Perſequutio ſive a leone, ſive a dracone nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ceſſat Eccleſiae, magis verò metuenda eſt quum fallit, quam quum ſaevit.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed by <hi>James Lindeſay,</hi> Printer to the Univerſitie of EDINBURGH. 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:58988:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58988:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE MAGISTRATS AND COUNCELLERS Of the moſt famous City of <hi>EDINBVRGH.</hi> SIR IOHN SMITH LORD PROVEST. ANDREW SIMSON, ROBERT ATCHISON, JOHN INGLISH, and GEORGE WALKER, Bailies. <hi>GEORGSVTIE Deane of Guild, and JOHN FAIRHOLME Theſaurer:</hi> And to the whole Councel of the flowriſhing Towne of <hi>Edinburgh:</hi> Grace here, and Glorie hereafter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a time to ſpeak, and a time to keep ſilence, ſaith the wiſe <hi>Preacher,</hi> in the <hi>3.</hi> of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes;</hi> the truth wherof, though it be acknowledged by all, yet the fitneſſe of the time of both, is greatly miſtaken, by many: For there are ſome that think it a time to ſpeak, when they ought to keepe ſilence, and others thinke it a time to be ſilent, when they ſhould ſpeake. It is ſaid in Hiſtorie, that<note n="(a)" place="margin">Guevara lib. <hi>4.</hi> di. principe cap. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Acaticus</hi> the Philoſopher, while he feaſted with his friends, being asked, wherfore he keped ſilence, when others did ſpeak, he anſwered, that it was no leſſe deficil to know when to ſpeak, than to know how to
<pb facs="tcp:58988:3"/>ſpeak. The Scripture telleth us that <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> wil have Chriſt to ſpeak, when he thinks it more expedient to keepe ſilence: and the Diſciples will have him to keepe ſilence, leaſt the Phariſees ſhould be offended, when hee thinks it better to ſpeak freely, that their faults may be reproved. The Greek Retorician admoniſhed his friend well,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Duo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendi tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra conſtitue unum de rebus tibi plane cognitis, alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum de ijs quae neceſsario ſunt dicenda, in his enim ſolis praeſtat ſilen tio oratio in alijs verota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere ſatius eſt quam loqui Iſocrates Ad demonicum.</note> 
               <hi>That he ſhould appoint to himſelf two times of ſpeaking, one of things whereof he himſelf had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect knowledge, and another of things which neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſhould be ſpoken, for in ſuch things ſpeach is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than ſilence, and in all other things it is better to be ſilent, than to ſpeake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One of the Romane writters relateth of a Senatour, Bloſius,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Quis Blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſium ſcelera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum putaſſet fuiſſe ſi tacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſet, quis non etsam ſapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, ſi pro ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitate tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris loquutus eſſet. Valerius maximus lib <hi>4</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> That none would have thought him wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, if he had holden his peace, and any man would have thought him wiſe, if he had ſpoken according to the neceſſitie of the time.</p>
            <p>If then the fitteſt time to ſpeake be, when the things that are ſpoken are needfull to be ſpoken, then it is a fit time to ſpeak when great danger is threatened and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous trouble apprehended: for by keeping ſilence great skaith and damage may be ſuſtained, and by ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſpeaking great profite and commoditie, may bee reaped, and tymous remedie provided. This chiefly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to faithfull Paſtors, who watch for the ſoules of people, for in the time of threatned perſecution they ſhould ſpeake to God by prayer, that his people may be protected, and they ſhould ſpeake to the people by good inſtruction, and ſound direction, that they may know how to carie themſelves in the time of danger and affliction, for as king <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> firſt fervently prayed to God, and then comfortably incouraged the people when they were threatened with hoſtill invaſion:
<pb facs="tcp:58988:3"/>So faithfull Paſtors muſt not looke how their ſpeaking may offend, or ſilence may pleaſe the enemies of the Truth, and oppreſſors of Gods people: But how much their ſeaſonable ſpeaking concerneth the honour of God, and the ſafetie of his people, for whom they muſt ſpeake to God, by fervent prayer,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Perpende quid dicturus es examina conſule interi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orem veritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſic profer ad exteriorem auditorem Auguſt in Pſal; <hi>4</hi>
               </note> and to whom they muſt ſpeake from God by the Oracles of his Word. And therefore (moſt wiſe and worthy Councellours) as this is the practice of all the faithful Paſtors in this land, to ſpeake to their people of ſuch things as concerne the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate, and condition of the land: I thought it was my part not to be deficient in ſo neceſsary a duetie, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeeing by divine providence, I have occaſion to preach in the moſt eminent Citie, though unworthie to preach in the obſcureſt Corner of the Kingdome. Be it knowne therefore to your Lo. that the occaſion of the preaching of this Sermon, to them that heard it, and the publiſhing of it, to ſuch as ſhall read it, wherein I have weakly deſcribed the cruell practices of the proud perſecutors of Gods people, the occaſion whereof I ſay, was the late troubles that our Nation hath ſuſtained by the violent invaſion of our unnaturall Countrey-man, whoſe pride and ambition hath ſo farre miſcaried him, that he hath troubled the people of God, and his owne Countrey-men, with bloudy cruelty, and horrible op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. It is well known, that once he did take part with the people of God, againſt their enemies, but now contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the oath which he ſwore in his Covenant, he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined againſt Gods people, with their open enemies, and ſheweth himſelfe unmindefull of the love that he ought to his Countrey,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Caedis ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c cumulo patriae per viſcera vadit Lucan. lib. <hi>7</hi>
               </note> through whoſe bowels he paſſeth with continuall ſlaughter. <hi>O quantum mututatus ab il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo hectore qui fuerat,</hi> ſo powerfull is pride and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:58988:4"/>to make a wonderfull change, and alteration in the hearts of men, from good to evil, and from evil to worſe, untill the extremitie thereof be ſuch, as cannot longer be ſuffered, but by divine juſtice, muſt needs bee puniſhed. And truly, the cruell courſes of this Cateline, are knowne to the world, but what his end ſhall be, is beſt knowne to God: one thing we know from divine Truth, that the cryes of the Elect ſhall ſpeedily be avenged. And as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith<note n="(f)" place="margin">Oppreſsio pauperis vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictam evo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat divinam mortem no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centis acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerat, aures divinas iugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inquietat Auguſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Fauſtum.</note> 
               <hi>The oppreſſions of the poor calleth for Gods vegeance, it haſtneth the death of the oppreſſor, and continually troubleth the ears of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I have taken the boldneſſe to dedicate this firſt fruit of my weak labours to your honourable protection for divers reaſons, firſt becauſe there is no Preacher that can have greater or nearer relation to any people then I have to you, being the ſonne of a Citizen borne in your Citie, bred up in your Schools of learning, and by divine providence theſe <hi>20.</hi> years imployed in the work of the Miniſtery amongſt you: in how great weaknes is known to God, and my ſelfe, but with what willingneſſe and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieneſſe it is known to you (my honourable Patrons and the reſt of my worthie Citizens. Secondly becauſe as God of his goodneſſe hath made this Citie the chiefeſt of this Nation, ſo hath he been pleaſed to furniſh you the preſent Magiſtrats, and Councellours with wit, and diſcretion, vertue, and pietie, which the exigencie of this dangerous time requireth in ſuch as are worthy of your places, and as the tree is known by the fruits, ſo the eminencie of theſe gifts ſhoweth foorth it ſelf in you by the ſingulare care that ye have to ſee the true Religion flouriſh in your Citie, to chariſh learning in all kinds of profeſſions of divine and humane literature:
<pb facs="tcp:58988:4"/>and in a word your Citiznes ought to be thankfull to God for your ſingulare diligence, in puniſhing of vice, and advancing of vertue. Seeing as the Romane Oratour could ſay,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Nec do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus nec reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publica ſtare poteſt ſi in e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nec recte fact is praemia extent ulla nec ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicia peccatis. Cicero lib. <hi>3.</hi> de natura. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum.</note> 
               <hi>No houſe or common-wealth can long continue, where there is no reward appointed for good workes, or puniſhment for evil:</hi> And one of the Latine Comicks could ſay,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Oppidum ſi incolae ſunt bene morati, pulchre mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitum arb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tror Plaus. in perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>That he did thinke a Citie well guarded whoſe Citizens were indued with good manners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe then being the reaſons of the didication of this firſt birth of my weake labours which hath come to the view of the world, to your honourable protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I humbly implore your favourable acceptance, for which I ſhall never ceaſe to pray to God for the health of your perſons, the proſpering of your weightie affairs and the wellfare of your flouriſhing Citie. And ſo ſhall remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lo. humble ſervant in Chriſt, to the uttermoſt of my power, even untill death. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> Archibald Skeldie.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:58988:5"/>
            <head>THE TABLE. HERE FOLLOWETH THE SUMME Of the purpoſes, which are ſet down in order.</head>
            <list>
               <item>FOur things are to be handled in the explaining of the words. Page <hi>2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Two ſorts of pride poſſeſſe and miſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the children of men. Page <hi>3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>This inward pride hath three bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Page <hi>3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pride breaketh outagainſt God four manner of wayes. Page <hi>7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pride againſt men breaketh out four manner of wayes. Page <hi>11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Proud parſecutors ariſe againſt Gods Saints for three reaſons. Page <hi>17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Saints of God when they are threatned by their proud enemies, may boldly pray to God for two reaſons. Page <hi>21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Prophet mentioneth the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of his enemies for two rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: Page <hi>24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Concerning our truſting in God, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers things are to be obſerved. Page <hi>27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>There is a twofold uſe to be remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the affembling of Davids e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. Page <hi>28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Covenanters ſhould lay three things to heart, when they hear of the aſſembling of their enemies. Page <hi>31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>While we pray for the Lords pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence againſt our enemies, we muſt looke to two things Page <hi>34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The enemies of the Saints are crueſt in three reſpects. Page <hi>35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When the enemies of David ſeek af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his ſoule, there are two things included. Page <hi>38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The conſideration of the cruelty of Davids enemies teacheth as a two fold uſe. Page <hi>40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>We ſhould avoyd crueltie and ſtudie to mercy for foure reaſons Page <hi>41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>We ſhould pray to God to be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from our cruel enemies for two reaſons. Page <hi>45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The perſecutors of the ſaints are ſaid not to ſet God before them in a three-fold reſpect. Page <hi>47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That a Chriſtian may ſet God before him <hi>4</hi> things are required. Page <hi>51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To look to the will of God as the rule of our actions includeth <hi>2</hi> things. Page <hi>51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>There are three reaſons wherefore a Chriſtian ſhould alwayes ſet God before him. Page <hi>55</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58988:5"/>
            <head>PSALME LXXXVI.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Verſe <hi>14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>O God, the proud are riſen againſt me, and the aſsem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of violent men have ſought after my ſoule; and have not ſet thee before them.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He preſent condition and ſtate of this our time, letteth us ſee what need wee have to underſtand the meaning of theſe words, for our inſtruction and comfort: For as the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> when hee penned this <hi>Pſalme,</hi> was perſecuted by powerfull and malicious enemies, from whoſe rage and furie, hee prayeth to God for deliverance: So, we being threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the like hoſtile invaſion, have need to crave by humble ſupplication, the Lords gracious and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable protection.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Pſalme</hi> is juſtly ſtyled, <hi>A Prayer of David,</hi> with every petition whereof, is joyned a motive argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to move the Lord to hear his prayer, and grant his requeſts; And becauſe the royall <hi>Prophet</hi> after his manner in the former verſes, hath beene mixing praiſe with prayer, he now ſubjoyneth two motive argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to move the Lord to grant him, both the peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which he hath put up in the former part, and is to put up in the latter part of this <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt of thoſe arguments, is taken from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the nature of his enemies, againſt whom he prayeth: And the ſecond; from the conſideration of the Nature of God, to whom he prayeth.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:58988:6"/>
            <p> For amongſt all things, betwixt which may be ſeene any kind of oppoſition, there cannot any two things be found more contrarie to other, than <hi>Davids</hi> perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, and <hi>Davids</hi> Protectour. His perſecuters are cruell, proud, and godleſſe <hi>Atheiſts;</hi> His Protector is a<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 86.15</note> mercifull and pitifull God, <hi>ſlow to anger, and of great kindneſſe and truth:</hi> Which maketh <hi>Ierome</hi> to ſay<note n="(a)" place="margin">Divinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis natura cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens eſt &amp; pia &amp; magis ad in dulgontiam, quam ad vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictamprona. Hieronimus in Pſal. <hi>118.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The divine Nature is gentle, and pitifull, more readie to pardon, than revenge.</hi> And therefore the <hi>Prophet</hi> comparing the gracious Nature of God, with the wicked nature of his enemies, he more earneſtly imploreth, and more confidently expecteth the Lords helpe and protection againſt the malitious rage of his mighty enemies.</p>
            <p>Now that wee may enter upon the words of the <hi>Verſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Foure things are to be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planing of the words.</note> wherein the <hi>Prophet</hi> deſcribeth the nature of his enemies, both in reſpect of their inward diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and outward converſation: There are four things to be exponded in order, together with the uſes that ariſe from the conſideration of them, firſt, How theſe proud men are ſaid to ariſe againſt <hi>Davids;</hi> For this the <hi>Prophet</hi> uſeth as a motive argument to prevaile with God, ſeeing he knoweth that proud men are ſo hatefull to God. Secondly, The enemies of <hi>David</hi> were not a few, but a great number, that are ſaid to aſſemble themſelves: and ſo the <hi>Prophet</hi> hath the more need of the helpe of God. Thirdly, The enemies of <hi>David</hi> were violent and cruell men, whoſe crueltie is manifeſted in <hi>ſeeking of his ſoule;</hi> To which in the nixt <hi>verſe</hi> is opponed, <hi>the pitie and mercie of God,</hi> and ſo this part of the argument is powerfull to obtaine the helpe of God. Fourthly, The groſſe <hi>Atheiſme</hi> of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of <hi>David,</hi> is expreſſed when hee ſaith, <hi>They ſet
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58988:6"/>not God before them:</hi> No wonder therefore that God caſt them behinde him, as afterwards ſhall be declared.</p>
            <p>In the handling of the firſt point,<note place="margin">Two ſorts of pride poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men.</note> there are two things likewiſe conſiderable, firſt, how the enemies of <hi>David</hi> are called <hi>proud men.</hi> And what ſort of pride is this wherewith they were poſſeſſed and miſcaried? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, What can be the reaſon wherefore the proud enemies of <hi>David</hi> ariſe againſt him? And all other proud perſecutors againſt the Saints of God.</p>
            <p>As for the firſt, there are two ſorts of pride where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with a great many of the children of men are poſſeſſed and miſcaried.</p>
            <p>The firſt may be called an inward pride, becauſe though it be knowne to God, <hi>from whom</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ierem. 16.17</note> 
               <hi>no iniquity is hid,</hi> yet it is not known to men, except,<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 26.45</note> 
               <hi>when the mouth ſpeaketh of the abundance of the heart,</hi> for ſo the pride of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> was often manifeſted. But ſo long as it is not outwardly expreſſed, it is no wonder though it be not known to others: ſeeing it is hid from the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hath it, for either he no more knoweth that pride ruleth in him, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 Chro. 26.20.</note> 
               <hi>Vzziah</hi> did know, that he was leprous, before he was violently taken from the altar by the high prieſt: Or elſe, which is worſe, he is ſo far from thinking this pride to be vice, which is to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided, that he imagineth it to be a ſingular vertue, which is to be cheriſhed: for this is one of the miſeries to which ſinfull men are ſubject in this world,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Fallit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim vitium ſpecie virtutis &amp; umbra. Iu ven. ſatyr. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That they are deceived with vice, under the colour of vertue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we muſt conſider that this inward pride hath three branches, firſt,<note place="margin">The inward pride hath 3. branches.</note> vvhen men thinketh either that they have the gifts and graces that they have not, or at leaſt, in a greater meaſure than indeed they have them.<note n="*" place="margin">Galat. 6.3.</note> 
               <hi>He that thinketh himſelfe ſome-thing, while
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58988:7"/>hee is nothing, is deceived:</hi> For as the emptie veſſels when they are touched, ſoundeth loudeſt, and the barren trees lift their branches higheſt: So where there is leaſt worth, there is uſually a greateſt conceit and opinion of worth: Hence it is that often-times men are puffed up with a conceit of righteouſneſſe, though they be unrighteous, as our Saviour ſpeaketh of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees, They are wiſe in their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, when their remedileſſe folly is manifeſted to others;</hi> according to the ſaying of <hi>Solomon, Hee that is wiſe in his owne conceit, there is more hope of a foole than of him.</hi> And in a word, they are puffed up with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of knowledge above other men, while they are repleniſhed with groſſe ignorance of things that are chiefly to be known, like the<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 7.49</note> 
               <hi>Phariſees that counted the people curſed that knew not the Law:</hi> yet they themſelves underſtood not the meaning of the Law: As vve may read in the 23. of <hi>Mattews</hi> Goſpel, and therefore an Ancient ſaid vvell,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Nulla prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptio perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſior quam de propria iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia aut ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia ſuperbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. O ſuperba praeſumptio! O praſumptuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa ſuperbia! Augu. de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Domini.</note> 
               <hi>No preſumption is more hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, than to be proud of our own righteouſnes and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, O proud preſumption! O preſumptuous pride!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Men are inwardly proud, when (though they be gifted above others) they acknowledge not their gifts to come from God, who ought to be praiſed for the beſtowing of them, and ſerved in the uſe of them; they finde the fruit, but ſee not the tree from whence it falleth, they ſee the water, but perceive not the fountaine from whence it floweth; they finde the gifts to be in themſelves, therefore they think them to be of themſelves, and from themſelves, for though they have nothing, but what they have received, they boaſt, as though they had not received. This maketh them to aſcribe the praiſe of the gifts to themſelves, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58988:7"/>to thinke they may uſe them at their pleaſure: <hi>They</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Habac. 1.16</note> 
               <hi>ſacrifice to their owne net, and burne incenſe to their owne yarne.</hi> As the firſt pride was preſumptuous, ſo this pride is ſacrilegious, becauſe it depriveth God of the praiſe and glory that is due to his Majeſtie. And therefore <hi>Gregorie</hi> well obſerved,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Qui bona accepta ſibi arrogant, de bonis dei con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Grego. in moralibus.</note> 
               <hi>That hee who afcribeth not to God the good things that he hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, fighteth againſt the Lord with thoſe good things that he hath received from the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Men are puffed up with inward pride, when, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit they acknowledge they have received gifts from God, and are daily craving benefits at his hand; yet they are filled with ſuch a conceit and opinion of their owne merits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at they thinke they deſerve whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they have received, they thinke the Lord no leſſe oblidged to them, than they are to him. The old <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> though they could purchaſe heaven by their owne good workes.<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 18.18</note> 
               <hi>Good Maſter, what good thing ſhall I doe to inherit eternall life,</hi> and ſo they needed not to be ſaved by the merits of another, who by their owne merits could ſave themſelves. The proud hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrits are angrie when they are not regarded of the Lord, as they thought they ſhould have beene.<note n="*" place="margin">Iſay 58.3</note> 
               <hi>We have afflicted our ſoules, and thou hath not ſeene it:</hi> greater pride than all this is found in <hi>Papiſts.</hi> In the opinion of their merits of <hi>Congruitie, Dignitie,</hi> and <hi>Condignitie,</hi> and in the workes of <hi>Supererogation,</hi> not remembring what our Saviour hath injoyned his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples to ſay,<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 17.10</note> 
               <hi>That whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they have done all they can do, they are unprofitable ſervants.</hi> For albeit the baſeſt man in the world may ſometime, well deſerve at the hands of the greateſt, and the worſe man at the hands of the beſt, yet neither the greateſt, nor the beſt man in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58988:8"/>vvorld can deſerve any good at the hand of God,<note n="*" place="margin">Lam. 3.22</note> 
               <hi>whoſe mercie it is that he is not conſumed,</hi> and a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mercy, that by Chriſts merits he is brought to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: who by his own merits procures nothing but endleſſe condemnation. Therefore it was well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by <hi>Origen,</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Vix mihi ſuadeo quod poſſit ullum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus eſſe quod ex debito dei remuneratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem depoſcat cum etiam hoc ipſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod agere aliquod poſſumus velcogitare, vel proloqui, ipſius dono, &amp; largitione fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciamus. Ori gen in cap. <hi>4.</hi> ad Koma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos.</note> 
               <hi>I hardly can bee aſſured that there can be any work that requireth reward of God according to debt: Seeing even that, that we are able to doe any good, or to thinke, or ſpeake any good. we are inabled and furniſhed thereto by the gift of God.</hi> Thus, much concerning the inward pride, vvhich is not here underſtood by the <hi>Prophet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I now goe on to ſpeak of the outward, which juſtly may be ſo be called, not becauſe they that are miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caried with it, ſeeme to bee proud, and are not, as ſometime it falleth out in counterfeit humility, when men ſeeme to bee humble, and are moſt proud: for there is greateſt pride in affected humility, vvhich made <hi>Socrates</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Dicebat Socrates An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtheni, per fiſsuram palij tui video in ivanitatem tuam Eraſ. lib. <hi>3.</hi> apopheg. <hi>56.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Philopher</hi> to ſay, <hi>That hee ſaw the pride of Antiſthenes through the hole of his Mantle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſolom</hi> was never prouder than in his counterfeit humility and courteſie to the people. And the pride of <hi>Caligula</hi> was well obſerved, vvhen he would needs ſerve his invited gueſts in proper perſon, vvhich did not beſeeme the majeſtie of a Prince, which maketh <hi>Bernard</hi> to cry out,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Glorioſa res humilitas qua ipſa quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia palliari ſe appetit ne vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſeat. Bern. de gradibus humilitatis.</note> 
               <hi>That humility muſt needs be a glorious thing, wherewith pride it ſelfe ſeeketh to bee covered, leaſt if it ſhould be ſeene, it ſhould be deſpiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is called an outward pride, becauſe though it be both bred and cheriſhed in the heart, yet it cannot ſo lurke, and containe it ſelfe there, but now and then it breaketh foorth in the lookes of the countenance, words of the mouth, and workes of the hand: ſo that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58988:8"/>albeit in reſpect of the inbiding of it, it is inward and known to God: yet in reſpect of the out-breaking of it, it becometh outward, and is made manifeſt to all people. Now this outward pride either breaketh out immediatly againſt God, to his diſhonour and offence, or elſe againſt men, to their prejudice, by diſgrace,<note place="margin">Pride break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out againſt God foure manner of wayes.</note> or skaith, or hurt. Pride immediatly againſt God break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth foorh foure manner of wayes: Firſt, by affecting equality with God. Secondly, by ſeeking to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped as God. Thirdly, by expreſſing a manifeſt contempt of God. Fourthly, by opponing the will of man to the reveiled will of God.</p>
            <p>Firſt I ſay, When creatures affect equality with God, which is impoſible to be attained, ſeeing there is no proportion betwixt the infinite Creator, and the finite creature: Betwixt the creature that hath a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and may have an end, and God, which is without beginning, and can have no end. It is juſtly ſuppoſed, that this was the ſin wherefore Sathan was throwne downe from heaven to hell, which made a learned <hi>Divine</hi> to ſay,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Superbia in coelo nata eſt, ſic velut immemor qua via inde cecidit illuc poſtea redire non potuit. Hugo lib. de anima.</note> 
               <hi>Pride was bred in heaven, but being unmindfull what way it fell thence, it never could returne thither.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And truly that may bee well applyed to Sathan, which in another ſenſe is applied to the king of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iſay 14.12, 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>How art thou fallen from heaven, O Lucifer! ſon of the morning, and cut down to the ground? Thou ſaideſt in thine heart, I will aſcend above the clouds, and I will belike the moſt High.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This venome of pride did the old <hi>Serpent</hi> ſpew in our firſt parents, who would needs be like God, and aſpyring to a perfection whereof they were not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they loſed that perfection, whereof God had
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58988:9"/>made them capable, as the <hi>Latine</hi> proverbe ſayeth,<note n="(i)" place="margin">Camelus cornua qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens amiſit aures. Eraſm. in adagtis.</note> 
               <hi>The Camel which ſeeking to have hornes, did loſſe, his eares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 When creatures ſeeketh to themſelves the worſhip that is due to God: Satan that was puniſhed for his firſt pride hath wonderfully been exerciſed in the practice of this ſecond for as<note n="*" place="margin">Iudges 9.5</note> 
               <hi>Abimelech</hi> uſurped the kingdom, which being offered, was refuſed by <hi>Gedion:</hi> So, though the good angels<note n="*" place="margin">Revel. 19.10 Revel. 22.9</note> juſtly refuſed worſhip, when it is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, the wicked ſpirits doe crave it, though it be not offered: For in ſo doing, they thinke they greatly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure the Majeſty of God, with whom it was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be equall.<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.20.</note> The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> telleth us, <hi>That the ſervice that was done to the idols of the Gentiles, was done to devils.</hi> And no wonder that Sathan ſeeke to bee worſhipped of mortall men, when hee durſt bee ſo malapert as to crave worſhip of Chriſt,<note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 4.9</note> 
               <hi>for which he promiſed him the kingdomes of the world.</hi> Sathan likewiſe that tempted our firſt parents to affect equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity with God; hath taught ſome of their poſterity to ſeeke to be worſhipped as God. Hiſtorie telleth us of ſome Kings and Emperours, that being unmindfull of their mortality, and humane frailty, neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that they were but pieces of living clay, and as crawling wormes in the ſight of their Maker, who though they were lifted above many men, yet were not exalted above humanity,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 82.7</note> 
               <hi>but behoved to die like men, and fall like the Princes.</hi> Yet I ſay, They durſt be ſo ſhameles &amp; arrogant, as to crave to be worſhipped, even while they yet lived: which was done to <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, and <hi>Caligula</hi> the Emperour. Others againe were not deſirous of this honour, till after their death, which was given to the Romane Emperours after the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58988:9"/>civill wars<note n="(k)" place="margin">Bella pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſuperis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt civiliae divos. Lucan. lib. <hi>7</hi>
               </note> betwixt <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompei.</hi> Others againe, though they did not crave this honour, yet refuſed it not, when it was offered, as the Scripture telleth us of <hi>Herod Agripa,</hi> of whoſe pride &amp; plague we read in the 12. of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> for he was not like <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> who though they did miracles, would not bee counted gods, and though he was trained up in the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> religion, he was not ſo well mannered as <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> the <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane</hi> king, of whom it is ſaid, <hi>That when the Embaſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of Phaſis, in the name of their Senat, offered according to their manner, to make him a god: he asked them by way of jeſt, If any of them could make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves gods, for they that could not deifie themſelves, could much leſse deifie another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Men are proud againſt God, when being igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the excellency of God, and the greatneſſe of his power: they expreſſe their contempt of God, by queſtioning his power, and charging him with weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as though they were able to hinder him to doe what he willeth; and he were not able to hinder them to doe what they will. The <hi>Syrians</hi> blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly ſaid,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Kings 20.23</note> 
               <hi>That though the God of Iſrael prevailed in the mountaines, he could not in the valleyes.</hi> And <hi>Senacherib</hi> would have <hi>Ezekias</hi> to know,<note n="*" place="margin">Iſay 36.15.</note> 
               <hi>That his God in whom he truſted, was not able to deliver him out of his hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This pride proceedeth of ignorance, for if thoſe proud men did know the Lord, as he is reveiled to his Saints, of whom it is ſaid,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 76.1.</note> 
               <hi>That the Lord is known in Iudah, and his Name is great in Iſrael,</hi> then they would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Lord to be Almighty:<note n="*" place="margin">Iſaiah 36.15</note> 
               <hi>With whom nothing is impoſſible, to whom nothing is difficill,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 76.1.</note> 
               <hi>See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58988:10"/>he can doe exceeding abundantly, above all that we can aske or thinke.</hi> Thence it is that <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note n="(l)" place="margin">Non enim ob aliud vocae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens, niſi quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid vult po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, eiuc vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas est ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſima pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas Aug lib. <hi>21</hi> de civitate dei. cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>God for no other reaſon is called Almighty, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he can doe what ever hee willeth, and his will is moſt full power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Rebellious ſinners expreſſe their pride againſt God, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they oppon their wicked wil, to the reveiled will of God, ſo that albeit they know what God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them to do, they are ſo addicted to pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that they will doe nothing to pleaſe the Lord, but make open profeſſion of diſobedience, and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: This was the pride of wicked <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that ſaid,<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>He knew not the Lord, neither would he let his people go.</hi> Of this pride, ſpeaketh <hi>Gregorie,</hi>
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">Cum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia vitia Den<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fugiant, ſola ſuperbiaſe Deo opponit. Greg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in moralibus.</note> 
               <hi>When all other vices fleeth from God, pride only opponeth it ſelf to God.</hi> But this is more clearly expreſſed by <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> when he ſaith,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Superbia est quaedam praeſumptio cum quis pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumit vel au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det homo abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> timore des fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere ea quae ſoit eſse contra Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> creatorem viz peccare, nam ſuperbia eſt initium omnis peccati. Aug. in Ioannem.</note> 
               <hi>Pride is a certaine preſumption, when any preſumeth, or when a man without the feare of God, dare doe theſe things, which he knoweth to be contrary to the will of his Maker, to wit, to commit ſin, for pride is the beginning of all ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much concerning the outward pride, which immediately breaketh out againſt God. Now let us ſpeake of it, as it breaketh out to the prejudice and hurt of men, in which ſenſe it muſt needs here be taken, when men, whoſe hearts are poſſeſſed with ſelfe love, and filled with a conceit and opinion of their owne incomparable worth, whereby either they thinke all others to be their inferiors, or would have them to be their inferiors, none to be their equals, much leſſe their ſuperiors. When men, I ſay, that are ſo diſpoſed, ſtrive as they finde occaſion to performe in action, what they have conceived of themſelves,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58988:10"/>in their owne conceit and opinion, that is, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their power, they may make all others their inferiors: This outward pride breaketh out againſt men, foure manner of wayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, By unequall eſtimating of injuries,<note place="margin">Pride againſt men breaketh out foure man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wayes.</note> vvhich ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they doe to others, or ſuffer of others. Secondly, By exalting themſelves above others that are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier than themſelves. Thirdly, By cruell oppreſſion of others, either by fraud or violence. Fourthly, By their diſdainfull carriage towards others, to vvhom they refuſed to doe theſe duties, which they are bound to performe.</p>
            <p>Firſt I ſay, in a moſt unequall eſtimating of wrongs and injuries, that they do to others, &amp; ſuffer of others; what ever be the nature of the wrong wherewith they injure others, they count it ſo light, that they thinke there is no cauſe of complaining: and ſay, <hi>That they need make little reparation, or none at all:</hi> but when they are any way injured of others, whither the injurie be reall, or ſuppoſed, they cannot finde ſufficient words to agredge the greatneſſe of it, they complain without meaſure of the grievouſneſſe of it, and are ſo deſirous to be avenged of it, that not a ſimple, but a ſevenfold reparation muſt ſatisfie their vindictive humour, and cruell affection, vvith boaſting <hi>Lamech</hi> in the fourth of <hi>Geneſis.</hi> All the wrongs that proud men do, in their account, are but motes, and feathers, but what they ſuffer, are talents of leed, and greater than mountaines. They have not learned of the heathen <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> to ſpeake to themſelves by the light of nature,<note n="(o)" place="margin">Vide ne al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri facias quod pati no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, &amp; alterius animum de tuo metiaris. Hierocles in carm. Pythag.</note> 
               <hi>See thou doe not to another, what thou thy ſelfe would not ſuffer, and meaſure another mans minde according to thine owne minde.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:58988:11"/>
            <p> Secondly, This pride breaketh out, when the haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſpirits of unworthie men ſetteth them forward by unlawfull meanes, to exalt themſelves above others, which are every way better, and more worthy than themſelves, like<note n="*" place="margin">3 Ioh. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Diotriphes, Which would have the preheminence,</hi> So<note n="*" place="margin">Iudges 9.2.</note> 
               <hi>Abimelech delt ſubtilly with the Shechemites, that he might rule over them.</hi> And <hi>Sheba</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 20.1</note> 
               <hi>taking occaſion of the diviſion of the people, cauſed a trumpet to be blowne: that he might be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.</hi> Thoſe haughty proud ſpirits never looke what they deſerve, but what they deſire, neither to the hability of gifts, wherewith God hath furniſhed them, but to the capacity, which they conceive in their own imagination: they reſt not content with the lot which <hi>Providence</hi> hath diſpoſed,<note n="(p)" place="margin">Cui placet alterius, ſua nimirum eſt odio ſcrs. Horat. Epiſt. <hi>34.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>But are ſo well pleaſed with the lot of their neighbours, that they are alwayes diſcontent with their owne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which letteth them never ceaſe from aſpyring to eminency of place and dignity above others, whereof, for the moſt part, they are altogether unworthy. Like the <hi>Spiders</hi> that climbe to the roofe of the houſe, and <hi>Flies</hi> faſh men by fleeing about their faces: when the hony <hi>Bees</hi> byde in their skeps, and about their flowers, untill men injoy the fruit of their labour: and like the<note n="*" place="margin">Iudges 9.15</note> 
               <hi>Bramble accepting the kingdome, which was refuſed by the fruitfull trees.</hi> So, perſons that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of place and preferment, are moſt deſirous of honour and preferment; and to this purpoſe ingyre themſelves in the favour of men; that by their meanes they may ſatisfie their pride in the attaining of their deſired honour: Whereas modeſt and worthy Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, doe patiently wait upon the calling of divine <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence,</hi> to whatſoever place and ſtation Gods wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58988:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath appointed to bring them. This degree of pridethen is ſo much the more conſiderable, becauſe it may daily be obſerved in all rankes and conditions of men whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Mans pride breaketh foorth by unjuſt and cruell oppreſſion of innocent and peaceable men, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſecret fraud, or open violence: For when invie &amp; ambition concurre in the hearts of proud men, as they cannot with patience indure the preferment of ſuch whom they thinke unworthier than themſelves: So they cannot reſt content, unleſſe they poſſeſſe the places of others, that are in greater honour than themſelves: albeit they may know them to be more worthy: And becauſe, they cannot winne to this deſired exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without the prejudice and hurt of others, they care not to climbe to the top of preferment by other mens ruine and fall, for as king<note n="*" place="margin">1 Sam. 20.31</note> 
               <hi>Saul</hi> told <hi>Ionathan</hi> his ſon, <hi>That he ſhould not reign, if David</hi> lived. So proud men aſſure themſelves, that they cannot riſe, unleſſe, others fall: nor live, unleſſe others die, nor proſper, except they periſh: vvhich maketh ambitious men neither to care what vvords they ſpeake, nor vvorks they doe, to further their ambitious deſignes, while they purpoſe to beare rule, and not to be ruled, to command, and not to be ſubject. Hence it was well obſerved by a learned man<note n="(q)" place="margin">Ambitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus non curat prodeſſe, glori. a tur praeeſſe, praeſumit eſſe meliorem quiae cernit ſe ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riorem, gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia loquitur, ſublimia cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat ſubeſſe non patitur praeeſſe molitur. Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. de vilit conditionis humanae cap. <hi>3</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He that is ambitious, is not carefull to profite others, but thinketh it his glory to be above others, he preſumeth that he is better, when he ſeeth himſelfe ſuperiour, he ſpeaketh great things, he think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth high things, he cannot endure to bee ſubject, he deviſeth how to be exalted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For where this ambitious pride prevaileth in the hearts of men, it will eaſily breake all bonds aſſunder
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58988:12"/>whatſomever, that poſſible might ſeeme to reſtraine it, proud <hi>Abſolom</hi> breaketh the very bonds of Nature, to compaſſe his ambitious deſigne: he firſt, inſinuateth that his father is careleſſe of the well-fare of the people, and then he conſpireth the death of his father with a great number of the people. Civill bonds hath likewiſe beene uncivily broken, for ſubjects have riſen againſt their princes, and ſo<note n="*" place="margin">2 King. 8.15</note> 
               <hi>Hazael</hi> killed his maſter to reigne in his ſteade: others likewiſe by pride and ambition have been open enemies to their countrie, which nature teacheth a man to love, <hi>as Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> ſayeth,<note n="(r)" place="margin">Patriam quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> amat, non quia mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, ſed quia ſua, Senec. Ep. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Not becauſe it is great, but becauſe it is his own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet thoſe ambitious men have greatly trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the peace of their countrie for no other reaſon, but becauſe they did ſee others preferred to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which God made more reſpected, and better beloved than them; whom therefore they did hate ſo deadly that in ſeeking their ruine and deſtruction, they were the Authors of great calamity that befell their country and Nation.</p>
            <p>But then it is worthily to be remarked that ſuch unnaturall enemies of their countrie have not eſcaped the hand of Divine Juſtice, but have beene plagued with viſible judgements in the ſight of the world, for either they have periſhed with ſudden and violent death, or by impriſonment, or baniſhment (a juſt reward of their treacherie, and barbarous enimitie) or they have beene ſo far from attaining their ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious deſignes and projects, that while they ſought for honour and glorie, they have incurred ſhame and ignominie, and while they promiſed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wealth and riches, they were plagued with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58988:12"/>povertie, and finiſhed their wretched lives in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and miſerie, that in them it may be obſerved<note n="(s)" place="margin">Quam parva tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris intervalla homines in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſo faſtigio collocant, &amp; eoſdem rurſus ad extremam miſeriam &amp; calamitatem redigunt. Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina in vita Pij ſecundi.</note> 
               <hi>That as in a ſmall ſpace of time they have beene ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to the hight of honour, in a ſhort time likewiſe they have beene redacted to extreame calamitie and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie.</hi> Many ſuch examples we may reade both in the Greeke and Romane hiſtorie, in the Turks and Jewiſh hiſtorie, ſome likewiſe in the Chronicles of our neighbour Nation, and moe in the Chronicles of our owne Nation, where we may reade of ſome miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented, and ambitious Noble-men, that were men of greater power and wealth within this Kingdome, than many of our Noble-men, that by pride and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, are become enemies to their Nation, for to the latter ſort can hardly be applyed, what <hi>David</hi> ſpake of <hi>Doeg,</hi> when he ſaid,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 52.7</note> 
               <hi>This is the man that truſted in the abundance of his riches.</hi> For I verily think that the want of this, maketh ſome of them ſo wilfull as they are. But thoſe Noble-men of whom our hiſtory ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, though once they were men, of great wealth, power, and honour, by reaſon of their Linage and Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, yet ſo ſoon as by raiſing of a ſeditious faction with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Countrie, or by joyning with the neighbouring enemies out of the countrie, they became troublers of the peace of their countrie, they did never afterwards thrive nor proſper, their wealth was impoveriſhed, their perſons were plagued, their houſes were ruinated, their honour laid in the duſt, and their poſterity ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate, that their memory is periſhed. For ſince Nature hath taught man, to love his countrie better tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his life, and to count it<note n="(t)" place="margin">Dulce &amp; decorum eſt pro patria ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri. Publius mimus in ſen tentiis.</note> 
               <hi>a ſweet and comely thing to die for his countrie:</hi> which made the noble <hi>Athenian Themiſtocles,</hi> though he was unthankfully requited for his ſervice
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58988:13"/>done to his countrie, &amp; honourably intertained by the <hi>Perſian</hi> king, the enemie of his countrie, yet he chooſed rather to die, than to further king <hi>Xerxes</hi> in a courſe that tended to the ruine of his countrie. Vpon the other part, I ſay nature teacheth a man to be greatly grieved if his countrie ſhall be troubled by others, and more to deteſt and abhor that hee ſhould bee the troubler thereof himſelf, ſeeing all ſuch unnaturall monſters are deteſtable in the ſight of God: who as they procure the juſt curſe and hatred of their people: ſo they eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape not the avenging hand of the righteous God, by whom their ambitious deſignes are diſſapointed, their honours turned unto ſhame, and while they greedily deſire the wealth of others, they loſt that which peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able they might have injoyed themſelves.</p>
            <p n="4">4 This outward pride breaketh forth, when albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it men that are proude, neither ſeeke ſuperioritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove others, neither affect equality with their ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, yet they carie themſelves diſdainfully towards ſuch as they thinke their inferiors, and refuſe to doe the duties that they are bound to performe to their inferiors by Charitie, to their equals by civilitie and humanity, and to their ſuperiors by loayltie. This kind of pride is moſt uſually accompanied with froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and contumacy, with wilfulneſſe and obſtinacie, ſuch proud men uſually are more wilfull, than wiſe, and leane more to their owne wit, than to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of God and men, that might proove more profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble both to them and to others.</p>
            <p>It was this pride that moved churliſh<note n="*" place="margin">1. Sam. 25.10.</note> 
               <hi>Nabal</hi> to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere the ſervants of <hi>David</hi> ſo churliſhly, and that made the Elders of <hi>Succoth</hi> and <hi>Penuel</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iudges 8.6.</note> 
               <hi>to refuſe helpe and ſuccour to Gedions armie.</hi> This pride not only
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58988:13"/>proveth hurtful to private men, who by their raſhneſſe and indiſcretion provocke men to anger and indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to ſeeke to be avenged of the contempt and injury they thinke done to them. But it proveth likewiſe more prejudiciall to many,<note n="(w)" place="margin">Quicquid delirant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges plectuntar. achivi. Hor. Epist. <hi>2.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>When infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors are puniſhed for the fault of their ſuperiors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is to ſay, <hi>when men are in place and authority in a countrey or citie they leane ſo much to their owne wit, that they deſpiſe the counſell and advice of others.</hi> not being like<note n="*" place="margin">2 King. 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>Naaman that heard the advice of his ſervant,</hi> nor like the Elders of<note n="*" place="margin">Sam. 20.20</note> 
               <hi>Abel, that received the advice of a wiſe woman,</hi> but<note n="*" place="margin">Sam. 20.20</note> rather thinke that their counſel ſhould be followed of all, and they ſhould be counſelled by none: by ſuch wilfull pride and proud wilfulneſſe, many good things are neglected which might profitably be done, and many evils ar commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted which after-wards proved hurtfull, and might well have beene avoided.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the pride wherewith <hi>Davids</hi> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were poſſeſſed.<note place="margin">Proud per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods. Saints for 3. reaſons.</note> Now let us conſider wherefore <hi>Davids</hi> proude enemies ariſe againſt him, and what can be the reaſons that move other proud perſecutors to riſe againſt the Saints of God, the reaſons are eſpecially three.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, <hi>Becauſe proud men of all others are moſt like Sathan, and are the chiefeſt ſubjects of his kingdome.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, <hi>Becauſe proud men ſee ſome excellencie in the Saints of God which is not in themſelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thirdly, <hi>Becauſe the ſaints of God cannot be mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to favour their wicked opinions, and follow their lewd practices</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt I ſay, <hi>becauſe proud men of all others are moſt like Sathan, and are the chiefeſt ſubjects of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:58988:14"/>For as the humble Saints are of all other men moſt like God, becauſe after their effectuall calling, they are renewed to his image, in holineſſe and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, &amp; as they only are the loyall ſubjects of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the King of<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 149.2.</note> 
               <hi>Sion in whom they rejoyce:</hi> So ſeeing Sathan is the firſt proud creature, and the author of all pride, that is found in creatures, ſo the more proud that any man be, he is the liker Sathan the author of pride. Proud men likewiſe are Sathans moſt loyall ſubjects<note n="*" place="margin">Iob 41.34.</note> 
               <hi>For he is a king over the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of pride,</hi> to him they doe moſt acceptable ſervice, beeing led captive at his will greatly pleaſing him in the plotting and performing of their proud and ambitious deſignes, whereby God is diſhonoured, his people, troubled and the kingdome of Sathan is inlarged. And therefore, as Sathan himſelfe had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tempt one of the Saints of God, then a thouſand others: ſo proud men that are the ſlaves of Sathan, take pleaſure to trouble the Saints of God<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 10.2.</note> 
               <hi>The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with pride doe perſecute, the poore</hi> that is by mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſcoffing, by railing, and reproaching, and by hurting them in their ſtats and bodies, as they find op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity and occaſion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Becauſe proud men ſee ſome worth and excellencie in the Saints of God, which is not in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> by reaſon of ſome eminent grace, or gift wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God hath endued them, which not only becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the object of their invie, but likewiſe the ſpurre of their pride, when they cannot endure that another ſhould have the good which they themſelves want, and cannot winne to, and will rather<note n="*" place="margin">Ierem. 11.9.</note> 
               <hi>that the tree ſhould periſh with the fruit before it ſhould ſtand to bear fruit</hi> that is to ſay, They wiſh rather that the gifted men
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58988:14"/>ſhould periſh, and their gifts be loſt, than that they ſhould ſee the manifeſtation of Gods gift in an other which they have not in themſelves. So the powerfull words, and mighty workes of Chriſt make him to be perſecuted by the proud rulers of the Jews leaſt his fame ſhould be the occaſion of their ruine,<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 11.49</note> 
               <hi>and the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans ſhould come and take away their place and their Nation.</hi> The proud enemies of <hi>David</hi> were his cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el perſecutors, becauſe they did ſee that God was with him, that great things were to be done by him, and that great honour was to be conferred upon him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Becauſe the Saints of God cannot be mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nor induced to favour the opinions of proud men, and aprove their doings, and follow them in their wicked practices and ſinfull courſes,</hi> for proud men doe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo preſume of their knowledge, wiſdome, and underſtanding, that they think they cannot erre, or elſe they are ſo wilfull that though they be convinced of their error, they will not be reclaimed, ſome-times likewiſe they are ſo violently ſet upon ſinfull courſes, that becauſe they look for pleaſure and profite in the proſecuting of them, that either they think them to be lawfull, and equitable, or though they be convinced of their unlawfulneſſe, yet they will ſtand to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of them, and obſtinatly maintaine them as if they were moſt agreeably to equity and reaſon, ſo that they become open enemies to all that will not walke in them, or any way diſalow them, For as men that goe abroad in the world and by reaſon of their imployment have occaſion to meet with people of divers humours they will ſometimes meet with a ſort of men, that if they can flatter them, and pleaſe their humours, ratifie their words, and approve their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58988:15"/>they will reſpect them as their brethren, and their deareſt friends. But if they ſhall finde fault with their words, or cenſure their fooliſh carrage, then they ſhall altogether abhorre their companie, and count them the baſeſt fooles and idiots in the world. No wonder it is then, that proud men perſecute the Saints of God, that are ſo farre from imbracing their erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous opinions, and approving their wicked carriage and lewd converſation, that either they are openly cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring, and reproving them, or elſe they altogether refuſe to be of one minde with them in their errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us opinions, and to walk in one way with them in their lewd and wicked courſes. This is the reaſon of the perſecution that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſuſtaine by <hi>Papiſts,</hi> where they live together, and this is the ground of this great combuſtion that is kindled in theſe king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, for there is no other reaſon wherefore the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants are ſo violently ſet againſt the Covenanters, but becauſe they cannot be of one minde, and opinion with them concerning the matter of State &amp; Religion, for that which the Malignants think and profeſſe to be a meane to propogate Religion, and ſettle the ſtate of the Kingdom, the Covenanters with better reaſon, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme to be the ſubverſion of the ſtate, and ruine of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>Now before I come to the ſecond thing conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in this Text, there is an uſe that I would gather fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the former conſiderations, which is both for our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and inſtruction, when proud perſecutors which have great power and authority amongſt men, ariſe to trouble the peace of the Church of God, by grievous oppreſſion and perſecution. Then the Saints of God may boldly have recourſe to God by earneſt prayer
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58988:15"/>in hope of a gracious deliverance from their eminent danger, &amp; that for two reaſons. Firſt, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they conſider how diverſly the Lord is affected towards his Saints, and towards their perſecutors. Secondly, when they conſider the event of the inſultatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their perſecutors. Firſt I ſay, when they conſider how diverſly the Lord is affected towards his humble Saints,<note place="margin">The ſaints of God whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are threatned by their proud enemies, may boldly pray to God for two reaſons.</note> and towards their proud oppreſſors, for he taketh the humble for his deareſt friends, &amp; the proud for his rebellious enemies.<note n="*" place="margin">Iſaiah 66.2.</note> 
               <hi>He is near to the humble, as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is to the houſe where he dwelleth,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 25.9.</note> 
               <hi>and a Maſter to the Scholer that he teacheth.</hi> But though he be near to the proud, in the inflicting of of his anger, he is far from them in the manifeſtation of his favour. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 128.6.</note> 
               <hi>That though the Lord, be high, he looks to the lowly, but he knoweth the proud afar off.</hi> And therfore <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note n="(x)" place="margin">Humiliats Deus appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquat, ab exaltato longe recedit, niſi quem ipſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us humiliatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exaltaverit. Aug. in Pſ. <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That the Lord draweth near to him that is humbled, but he goeth farre away from him that is exalted, except he be one whom the Lord hath firſt humbled, and afterwards exalted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord multiplieth upon the humble his grace and his favour,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>For when they humble themſelves he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth to exalt them, and he exhorteth them to humble them ſelves, that he may exalt them: to him they may pray confidently,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal 86.1.</note> 
               <hi>under the ſenſe of their needines &amp; poverty.</hi> And therefore as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith,<note n="(y)" place="margin">Magna virtus hum ili tatis, cui ipſa dei mateſtas ſe tam facile in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinat. Bern. ſermo <hi>85.</hi> in canticum.</note> 
               <hi>That great is the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of humility, to which the Lord ſo eaſily inclineth his Majeſtie. But as the Lord compaſſeth the humble with his favour, ſo he purſueth the proud with his rath and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure.</hi> The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal 86.1.</note> 
               <hi>That he plentifully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeth the proud doer,</hi> for uſually when he puniſheth their pride, he abateth their power, and plagueth their perſons. One of the <hi>heathen</hi> could ſay,<note n="(z)" place="margin">Superbos ſequitur ultor a tergo Deus. Sen. in Her. furente.</note> 
               <hi>That God the revenger followeth proud men at the back:</hi> But the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58988:16"/>telleth us, <hi>That the righteous Lord ſtricketh them upon the face.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iſaiah 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>When he powreth ſhame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon all that are haughty,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 18.27.</note> 
               <hi>and caſteth downe the countenance of them that looke proudly.</hi> And the <hi>Prophet Iſay</hi> fore-telling the deſtruction of <hi>Moab,</hi> He ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Iſaiah 16.6</note> 
               <hi>We have heard of the pride of Moab.</hi> And the ſaying of <hi>Solomon</hi> is worthy of obſervation, <hi>That pride goeth before a fall, and a high minde before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The Saints of God at ſuch a time may confidently pray, when they conſider the nature and event of the inſultation of the proud perſecutors, how hatefull it is to God, how hurtfull to themſelves, whom for a time it pleaſeth: how comfortable in end it is to the Saints of God, to whom at firſt it ſeemeth to be fearfull and terrible; for when the proud op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors of the Church of God, have a purpoſe to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble their peace by ſome grievous perſecution, if they ſee any likelyhood or probability, that they can bring their purpoſe to paſſe, then ſuch is their untimous foly, that as the proverbe ſaith, <hi>They begin to ſing the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph before the victory, and to ſell the Bear skin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Bear be ſlaine:</hi> they threaten to execute what ever their malice can deviſe againſt the Saints of God, as if their power were ſo ſtronge, that they could not be reſiſted, and their wiſedome ſo deepe, that it could not be diſappointed, and their purpoſes ſo ſure, that they could not be overturned: Now when they thus begin to inſult by blaſpheming, railing, and threatning, then the Saints of God betake themſelves to prayer, and cry,<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 4.29.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, behold their threatnings,</hi> this prayer ſo prevaileth with God, that he maketh a ſudden change and alteration, for when the Saints of God
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58988:16"/>are brought loweſt, and the pride of their enemies ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced higheſt, then it is time for the Lord to worke ſuch a change, as both declareth the glory of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, juſtice, and power: When like the nailes of the wheele of <hi>Seſoſtris</hi> his chariot, that which was high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in a moment, becomes loweſt, and that that was loweſt, is advanced higheſt. Therefore we have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to thinke, that in the beginning of this combuſtion wherewith now theſe kingdomes are ſet on fire, many of the Saints of God found matter of great comfort, and a wonderfull ground of hope, that the enemies of the cauſe of Chriſt ſhould not proſper, and the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters</hi> ſhould be comforted, and graciouſly deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when they did heare of the untimous and fooliſh in ſulting of their proud enemies, that did promiſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory to themſelves, before they did fight, and were dividing Lands, diſtributing offices, skaring Cities, and killing all that ſhould make oppoſition, before that either they were vanquiſhed or invaded: for as it was a preſage of the <hi>Syrians</hi> overthrow,<note n="*" place="margin">2. Kings 20 11.</note> 
               <hi>when putting on their Armour, they boaſted as though they had put it off:</hi> and as it was a preſage of the ruine of <hi>Senacherib,</hi> and his army, when he boaſted ſo much of his power and victory.</p>
            <p>And as our Hiſtory telleth us, that the hudge ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond of <hi>England,</hi> was vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a handful of our Nation, who ſo preſumed of the certainty of his victory, that before hee entred the Countrey, he devided the lands, and appointed the King and his Nobles to ſeverall torments, and brought a <hi>Poet</hi> in his company to deſcribe his victory, who afterwards, being taken amongſt other captives, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in verſe the victory of his enemies.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:58988:17"/>
            <p> In later times we know how the army of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> was overthrown, that was called, <hi>The invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Armado.</hi> And truly the enemies of our Church and Kingdome, may learne to know by their ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full experience, that ſuch untimous and proud inſulting hath beene an evident preſage of their juſt confuſion, and a manifeſt fore-token to the people of God, of their unſpeakable comfort, and gracious exaltation, for when the pride of the wicked, and the prayer of the godly come together before the Lord, the one cryeth for ſpeedy juſtice to puniſh the wicked, and the other for timous mercy,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 32.10.</note> 
               <hi>to compaſſe ſuch as put their confidence in God,</hi> as wee may ſee in the pride of <hi>Senacherib,</hi> and the prayer of <hi>Ezekias</hi> the 37. of the propheſie of <hi>Iſaiah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Prophet mentioneth the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of his enemies for two reaſons.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now come we to the ſecond thing conſiderable in the enemies of <hi>David,</hi> when he ſayeth, <hi>that they aſsem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelves together.</hi> The Prophet maketh mention of their aſſembling for two reaſons: firſt for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Gods power, ſecondly, that he may declare his truſt and confidence, which he had in God.</p>
            <p>Firſt I ſay, for the glory of Gods power, for the weaker that the defendant party be, and the ſtronger that the aſſailing partie be, the power of the defender of the weaker againſt the ſtronger, is knowne to be the greater: the Scripture telleth us that king <hi>AchaZ.</hi> whoſe armie was miſerably foyled by the king of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was greatly affrayed, when he heard of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the kings of <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but then the power of the king of <hi>Aſhur</hi> was greater, that both defended <hi>Achaz</hi> and vanquiſhed his enemies. Hiſtorie telleth us <hi>that when the city of Conſtantinople was hardly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged by the hudge armie of Bajacet King of the Turkes
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58988:17"/>and the Greek Emperour could obtaine no help at the hands of Chriſtian Princes that were at variance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, he implored the help of Tamberlane king of the Tartars, who forced the King of the Turkes, to raiſe his ſeige, and put his armie to route, and tooke himſelfe captive, and ſo the power of the King of the Tartars, was knowne in delivering the weake Emperour of Greece, from the puiſſant king of the Turkes.</hi> The ſame way the power of God Almightie is manifeſted, when his Saints and ſervants are brought to extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that they can neither helpe themſelves, nor have help of others, againſt their many and mightie perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors: he that manifeſted his power in<note n="*" place="margin">2. Cor. 12.9</note> 
               <hi>Pauls weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse in the houre of temptation,</hi> declareth his power in the protecting of his Saints in time of perſecution.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Praeſidia ſua non nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit Deus ſuis in neceſsitato poſitis. Lyra. in Pſ. <hi>91.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>For the Lord will not deny his ſafe guard to his Saints while they are ſtraited with neceſſitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But graciouſly helpeth them, when they are redacted to greateſt extremity: remarkable is that example of <hi>Ezekias</hi> and his people; the armie of the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> was known to be great, <hi>Ezekias</hi> was ſenſible of his weaknes, that was not unknown to his enemie,<note n="*" place="margin">Iſai. 33.5, 8</note> 
               <hi>which told him that he had neither riders for horſes, nor coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell for war,</hi> but the power of God that protected <hi>EZe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kias</hi> was manifeſted, not only in promiſing him ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but likewiſe in the performing of his ſafety in the deſtruction of his enemie. <hi>EZekias</hi> that was ſo weake in the ſight of <hi>Senacherib,</hi> ſeemed fooliſh in holding out a walled city againſt him, but he would have judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him mad, if he had hazarted to come in open field againſt him, becauſe he ſhould have beene like the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie young ſon of king <hi>Priamus.</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Infaelix puer atqne impar con greſsus Chilli. Virg. lib. <hi>1,</hi> Aeneid.</note> 
               <hi>Who would needs fight with valiant Achilles.</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:58988:18"/>Yet the power of God was magnified, whoſe bridle was in the lips of <hi>Senacherib,</hi> that he could not further goe beyond his permiſſion, than an horſe can goe but where his rider pleaſeth. The Church of God in the 83. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> complaineth of the confederacy of many enemies, who not only ſought the wracke of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when they ſay,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 38.4.</note> 
               <hi>Let us root out Iſrael from being a Nation,</hi> but their pride breaketh out againſt the Lord himſelfe, when they ſay,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 38.12</note> 
               <hi>Let us take for our poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Manſions of God:</hi> whoſe deſtruction the Church craveth by humble prayer that God may be magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his glorious power.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>Prophet</hi> mentioneth the aſſembling of his enemies, to declare his truſt and confidence in God, for the multitude of his enemies is ſo farre from chaſſing him from God, that it maketh him to run the more to God, by earneſt prayer and ſettled confidence, who as by his power he is able to protect him, ſo by his<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 32.1.3</note> 
               <hi>mercy he will compaſſe him, that putteth his truſt and confidence in him,</hi> for the <hi>Prophet</hi> well knew how powerfully this argument would prevaile with God, that he that is purſued by many enemies, and truſteth in God, ſhould be protected by the power and mercy of God. <hi>Humanity</hi> will teach men not to forſake nor betray, but rather to protect to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of their power, ſuch as put confidence in them, and commit their lives to their care. As it is ſaid in the Hiſtorie of <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> king of <hi>Perſia,</hi> which ſet a <hi>Sparrow</hi> at libertie, which fled to his boſome, &amp; would not give it a prey to the <hi>Hawk,</hi> he uttered theſe words in the audience of his Princes, <hi>As I have not delivered this Bird to bee a prey to its enemie, ſo will I never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceive, but protect the man that truſteth in mee:</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:58988:18"/>Much more, I ſay, will the tender mercie of our gracious Lord, move him graciouſly to protect<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 53.1, 4</note> 
               <hi>all thoſe that put their truſt under the ſhadow of his wings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the deepe conſideration, and comfortable ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, whereof we have divers remarkable things ſet downe in holy Scripture.<note place="margin">Concerning our truſting in God, diverſe things are to be obſerved.</note>
            </p>
            <p>As firſt, that every one of Gods Saints ſhould well obſerve what ſingular experience they have found of Gods favourable protection, which maketh <hi>David</hi> not to be afrayed of the multitude of his enemies, when he conſidereth how hee hath beene delivered from the furie and rage of his enemies.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Baſil</hi> well explaineth his meaning in the 27. <hi>Pſa.</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Quoniam tantum aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ilij divine experimentum accepi ut eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amſi duplo vel triplo plures hostes me obruere co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantur hac tamen ſpe mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus infracto animo obſiiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> malis. Baſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in ſcoliis in Pſal. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Becauſe I have received ſo great experience, and proofe of divine helpe that albeit twiſe or thriſe ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny preaſe to overwhelme me, yet being guarded by this hope, I will withſtand all thoſe evils with invincible courage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly. The Lord himſelfe hath exhorted his people to truſt in him, with a promiſe of ſecurity and ſafety. The 20 of the ſecond of the <hi>Chronicles.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 34.23.</note> 
               <hi>Truſt in the Lord, and yee ſhall bee eſtabliſhed, believe his Prophets, and ye ſhall proſper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, If we looke to the experience of his Saints, it may be juſtly ſaid,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 22.5.</note> 
               <hi>None of them that truſt in him, ſhall be deſolate,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 22.5.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe they were alwayes delivered that truſted in him, and our fathers that truſted in him, were not aſhamed:</hi> And therefore we muſt not with-draw our confidence from God, when we ſee no appearance of help at the hands of men; but ſo much the more relie on him, with truſt and confidence, whoſe reliefe commeth uſually, when there is leaſt appearance. It is our part that are Chriſtians to ſay
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58988:19"/>as <hi>Euſeb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> bringeth in <hi>Philo</hi> the <hi>Iew,</hi> ſpeaking to his countrey-men, when <hi>Caligula</hi> the <hi>Emperour</hi> would not hear their petition, but commanded them to avoid his preſence.<note n="(d)" place="margin">Bono ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo eſſe debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus quibus i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus eſt Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. Neceſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim est adeſſe auxilium di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinum, ubi ceſsat huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Euſeb. Eccleſ. hiſtor. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>We ſhould be of good courage</hi> (ſaid <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo</hi>) <hi>at whom Caius is angrie, becauſe of neceſſitie divine helpe will bee preſent, when humane helpe ceaſeth.</hi> From the conſideration of the aſſembly of <hi>Davids</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, we are to remarke a two-fold uſe,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Here wee may obſerve that albeit the enemies of <hi>David</hi> be proud, and by reaſon of their pride and ambition, have their mutuall diſſentions and emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: yet they can combine themſelves to be <hi>Davids</hi> perſecutors.<note place="margin">There is a two fold uſe to be remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſembling of <hi>Davids</hi> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This may ſeem the more ſtrange and admirable, if we conſider the nature of proud men, in ſo far as they are proud, for they preſume of their owne worth, and think all others to be baſe and contemptible, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume of their own wit, ſo that nothing in their eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can be wel ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or done, but their own words &amp; their own works, or elſe what one way or other pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth their humours, they ſo look to their own honour and wealth, that they care not for the wrack and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of others. It is a wonder then, that in any reſpect they can aſſemble with others, that in theſe reſpects do ſeparate themſelves from all others, &amp; yet we ſee that though <hi>Pilate</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> be mutuall enemies they can be friends when Chriſt is crucified. And though there be mutuall hatred betwixt the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Sadduces</hi> they can conſpire when Chriſt is perſecuted. There was no greater confuſion at the building of the tower of <hi>Babel,</hi> nor is in the <hi>Romane</hi> Church amongſt their religious orders: yet all of them can conſpire againſt the profeſſion and profeſſours of the Truth.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:58988:19"/>
            <p> The reaſon then of the combining of the proud perſecutors of the Saints of God, may be expreſſed in a plaine compariſon. A great king that is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of diverſe Countries, and Provinces, though thoſe Countries differ in their Languages, and in their maners, though ſome of them invie others priviledges, and contemne others baſenes, yet being imployed in a warre againſt the kings enemies, they can all make up the bodie of one Armie, as if they were Citizens of one Citie, we know that perſecution is the worke of Sathan, the king of pride: though it be performed by men that are the children of pride, the perſecution of the Saints is hatched in hell by Sathan, before it be either threatned, or executed by men upon earth.<note n="*" place="margin">Revel. 12.15</note> 
               <hi>This is the water that cometh out of the mouth of the Dragon, to drown the woman and her ſonne;</hi> that is a fruit of the enimitie<note n="*" place="margin">Geneſ. 3.15.</note> betwixt the <hi>ſeed of the ſerpent and the ſeed of the woman.</hi> The proud perſecutors of the Saints of God, are ſet a work by Sathan, the king of the children of pride, about one worke, for one end, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the kingdome of Chriſt, albeit it be true, that wicked men, that have hand in the buſineſſe, have their owne wordly devliſh and divers other reſpects, in the ſatisfying of their wicked humours, ambition, cruelty, and covetouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>But to bring the application nearer home, it may be queſtioned, How can it be thought, that all the Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant partie, which perſecute the Covenanters in theſe Kingdomes, doe ſervice to Sathan for one end, ſeeing many of them make profeſſion, that all they doe, is for the propagation of true Religion? To this I anſwere, that ſeeing there is a great aſſembly of divers ſorts of perſons againſt the profeſſors and defenders of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58988:20"/>truth in their kingdoms, that is to ſay, Profeſſed <hi>Papiſts</hi> and Malignant <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> Concerning the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> we may juſtly ſay, <hi>They carie themſelves more wiſely in keeping of ſilence, than if they ſhould ſpeak,</hi> for it is well known to God and their own conſciences, &amp; to all that know them, that the maine end of all their doings, is to get liberty to profeſſe their own Religion, and to finde opportunitie to extirpate the Proteſtant Religion. But the Malignant Proteſtants doe carie themſelves more Antichriſtian like in the buſines, than the <hi>Papiſts</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, for we know that the name of Antichriſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth one that ſaith, <hi>He is for Chriſt, and yet doth againſt Chriſt.</hi> ſo thoſe men make profeſſion, that all their care is for the advancing of the true Religion, when in the mean time all their courſes &amp; projects tend to the ruine of true Religion, and erecting of idolatrie and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And as Hiſtory relateth of <hi>Didius Iulianus,</hi> who ſucceeded <hi>Pertinax</hi> in the <hi>Romane Empyre,</hi> which he attained not by the conſent of the <hi>Romane</hi> Senate, but bought it with money that he promiſed to the <hi>Preto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Souldiers, when this man after the cuſtome of the <hi>Romane Emperours</hi> would be ſtyled the father of his Countrie, there was a writting ſet upon the gate of his palace by night<note n="(e)" place="margin">Didius Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianus non pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter patriae ſed emptor, vendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor &amp; proditor patriae mellifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium hiſtor.</note> 
               <hi>Didius Iulianus is not the father of his Countrie, but the buyer and ſeller, and betrayer of his Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So thoſe <hi>Malignant Proteſtants</hi> who profeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be furtherers of Religion, and defenders of their Country, are by their lewd and wicked pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices declared to be enemies to the Truth, and trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to their Countrie.<note place="margin">The Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ters ſhould lay three things to heart when they heare of the aſſembling of their enemies.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond uſe which hereof ariſeth when the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters of <hi>Britain</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland</hi> hear of the aſſembling
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58988:20"/>of the <hi>Malignant</hi> enemies from divers quarters: there are three things which earneſtly they ſhould lay to heart, firſt they ſhould ſtudy by all means to keep peace amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt themſelves. Secondly they ſhould hinder by all means the enemies which are in divers places to come together into one place. Thirdly they ſhould intreat the Lord by prayer to be preſent in the aſſemblies of his Saints, that ſo they may be protected againſt the aſſemblies of their enemies. Firſt I ſay, they ſhould carefully ſtudie to keepe peace amongſt themſelves, that is to ſay, they ſhould labour to be of one minde in the mater of Religion, and in the exerciſe of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and worſhip of God, they ſhould mutually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend one another, according to thair Covenant, they ſhould remove all excuſes from them, which may hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them to advance the Cauſe of Chriſt, none that hath power ſhould pretend weakneſſe: nor that hath wealth ſhould prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d poverty, but every zealous Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſhould count it his honour &amp; happines that God hath furniſhed him with habilitie, and by his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence offered him opportunity to honour Chriſt, and to advance his Kingdom.<note n="*" place="margin">Coloſ. 3.15</note> Chriſtians that are called to peace in one body, ſhould let the peace of God rule in their hearts at all times, but eſpecially when their peace is troubled by cruell perſecutors. <hi>Abraham</hi> thought it not time<note n="*" place="margin">Geneſ. 13.8.</note> To diſcord with <hi>Lot</hi> in the land of the <hi>Amorites</hi> Hiſtorie telleth us that though the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and <hi>Thebanes</hi> had their mutuall jealouſies, yet they packed up all their diſſentions, when they were invaded by <hi>Philip</hi> king of <hi>Macedone</hi> the common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of the libertie of <hi>Greece.</hi> It is a lamentable matter<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 16.8.</note> 
               <hi>that the children of this world in their own genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould be wiſer than the children of light.</hi> At this
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58988:21"/>time all the covenanted people of the Lord ſhould be carefull to keep peace amongſt themſelves, partly when they conſider that uſually diſtraction is a dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous preſage of deſtruction, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticke Hiſtorie obſerveth that the diſſenſion betwixt the Eaſterne and the Weſterne Church was the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of the tenth perſecution: and partly, becauſe vnion maketh ſtrength, but deviſion bringeth weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>There is no Nation under Heaven, hath more reaſon to lay this to heart, then we of this <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> We read that when <hi>Antonius</hi> was vanquiſhed by <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> while he lay a dieing by his owne deadly wounds he ſaid to <hi>Cleopatra Queene of Egypt, It is no ſhame for a Romane to be vanquiſhed by a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane:</hi> but truly it is the miſerie and diſhonour of this Kingdome, that SCOTLAND hath beene ſo frequently vanquiſhed by <hi>Scots,</hi> for our Hiſtory telleth us that the moſt powerful forraine people that ever invaded this Kingdome, was never able to vanquiſh this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without the combining of treacherous &amp; miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented ſubjects amongſt our ſelves. Of whom it may be ſaid as the <hi>Greek</hi> Oratour ſpake of the beſieged <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynthians,</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Ibi alij ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes propulſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, alij ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem prodebant Demoſt thenet oratione. <hi>3.</hi> Philippica.</note> 
               <hi>That while ſome valiantly were repulſing the enemies, others were treacherouſly betraying the Citie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if we be true to our ſelves, and keepe that peace which we have ſworne in our <hi>Covenant,</hi> and is recommended to the diſciples of Chriſt, wee need the leſſe to care for all the enemies of the Cauſe of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when the people of the Lord heare of the aſſembling of their enemies, they ſhould labour what
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58988:21"/>in them lyeth, to hinder them that are in ſeverall pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to come together into one place. It was wiſely done of the <hi>Romans</hi> to fight with the armie of <hi>Hazru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball,</hi> before they joyned with the armie of <hi>Hannibal</hi> for otherwiſe the later troubles of <hi>Italie</hi> had beene greater than the former. It is a great deale more ſafe to deal with the ſeverall parts of an Armie, than with the compleat body of an Armie, as the hiſtory of our Nation telleth, of one of our Noble men, who with eight thouſand of our people, in the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, King of <hi>England,</hi> vanquiſhed in one day, thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thouſand of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, that were devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in three bands, which would have beene more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieill, if all had beene joyned together. We know that as many burnes may make a great river: ſo many hands joyned together, may make a ſtrong and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full invaſion: the ſmaleſt enemie is not to be contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, becauſe his power may grow if he be altogether neglected and diſpiſed, as <hi>Amorath</hi> the ſixth king of the <hi>Turks,</hi> told his ſonne <hi>Mahomet</hi> concerning <hi>Scanderbeg,</hi> the prince of <hi>Epirus,</hi> who increaſſed in power, becauſe he was neglected and contemned. It was well ſaid by a <hi>Greeke</hi> writter,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Qui ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem ſpernit ſibi periculum accerſit. Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidides. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That whoſoever contemneth his enemie, bringeth danger to himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wiſe people ſhould doe with their combining ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as Chriſtians ſhould doe with ſinne, which in the beginning is to be reſiſted, leſt afterwards it grow ſo ſtrong, that it car not be reſiſted. It was worthily ſaid by a learned man,<note n="(h)" place="margin">In rebus omnibus qui maximum malum vitare cupit, neceſſe eſt, ut malum exoriens ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguat. Oſor. lib. <hi>4.</hi> de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutione Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis.</note> 
               <hi>That in all things he that would avoyd the greateſt evil, muſt needes extinguiſh the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It greatly concerneth the peace and preſent ſaftie of this Nation, to make timous oppoſition to the armies
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58988:22"/>of our enemies, before they be ſtrengthned by a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter faction as<note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Ioab purſued Sheba, the ſonne of Bichri before he could gather a greater companie.</hi> And truly we have reaſon to bleſſe the Lord for that ſingulare care and diligence that he hath put in the hearts of our worthie Noble-men and commanders, that are conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of peace, that they have ſo timouſly oppoſed the inſulting enemie, that no ſooner was his power in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, but als ſoone it decreaſed: like<note n="*" place="margin">1 Kings 16 15.</note> the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Zimri</hi> that laſted for a week.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, when we heare of the aſſembling of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers people from divers quarters, our humble pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhould be to the Lord,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 89.7.</note> 
               <hi>That he would be preſent in the aſsemblie of his Saints,</hi> that ſo they may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected and defended againſt the aſſemblies of their cruell enemies.<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 8.31.</note> 
               <hi>If God be one our ſide, who is againſt us?</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Chro. 13.10.</note> 
               <hi>Abijam was more incouraged that God was with his people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">While wee pray for the Lords preſence againſt our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, wee muſt looke to two things,</note> 
               <hi>than he was afrayed of the hudge number of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboams armie which were againſt his people.</hi> But while we thus intreat the Lord by prayer, we muſt looke well to two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That we feare not exceſſively nor be faintheart, ed, when we are fewer in number, ſeeing it is alike to the Lord<note n="*" place="margin">1 Sam. 14.6.</note> 
               <hi>to vanquiſh by few as by many,</hi> according to the frequent paſſages that we reade of this purpoſe in the book of the <hi>Iudges,</hi> &amp; in the Books of the <hi>Kings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Though by Gods providence our num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber be greater, yet we muſt not leane to the ſtrength of man, but to the help &amp; aſſiſtance of God: for neither the greatnes of number, nor the goodnes of a cauſe for which they fight, will make a people prevaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginſt their enemies that hath greater confidence in their own ſtrength than in the help of God.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:58988:22"/>
            <p> I verily thinke that when <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> was threatned by his enemies, he could have raiſed a greater Armie nor all the kings that were his enemies, ſuch a number as I think all the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> conbined, could not bring the like number to the fielde, and yet he ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">2 Chro. 20.12</note> 
               <hi>Lord we know not what to do, but our eyes are towards thee:</hi> for as he knew that he was threatned by his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, without the Lords approbation, ſo he knew that though he had a greater number, he might be vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Lords permiſſion.<note n="*" place="margin">2 Chro. 20.12</note> 
               <hi>Chariots and horſes may runne to the battell, but the Lord of hoſts giveth victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> wherefore he imploreth the help of the Lord and putteth his truſt and confidence in him, by whoſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſiſtance and power the greateſt number may be vanquiſhed, as well as the leaſt, and without whoſe helpe and aſiſtance, the greateſt number may be vanquiſhed by the leaſt. But if we ſhall finde acceſſe to God by prayer, then whenſoever we are threatned by our enemies, we may looke for protection and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, according to the obſervation of <hi>David.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 56.9.</note> 
               <hi>When I crie then mine enemies ſhall be turned backe, this I know, for God is for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let us ſpeake of the third thing conſiderable in the enemies of <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Saints are cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el in three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</note> he calleth them <hi>violent and cruell men that ſeeke after his ſoule,</hi> where we are to obſerve, that the enemies of Gods Saints and ſervants may well be called violent and cruell, and that in three reſpects: firſt in reſpect of their affection, ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in reſpect of their words, thirdly in reſpect of their actions.</p>
            <p>Firſt I ſay, in reſpect of their affection, for the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred they beare to the Saints of God, as it is unjuſt in reſpect of the ground of it, and deadly in reſpect of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58988:23"/>the project, ſo it is irreconciliable in reſpect of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of it. Firſt I ſay, it is unjuſt in reſpect of the ground of it, for they hate the Saints of God for the excellent graces which they ſee in them.<note n="*" place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>Cain</hi> ſlew his brother <hi>Abell,</hi> becauſe his own works were evil and his brothers good, and therfore one ſaid well,<note n="(i)" place="margin">Si non eſſet claritudo ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum, non ſurgeret invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia impiorum. Lyra. cap. <hi>4.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>1</hi> Ioan.</note> 
               <hi>If the brightneſſe of the Saints did not ſhine, the invie of the wicked ſhould not ariſe againſt them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, it is deadly, in reſpect of the project of it, for wicked men deſire the utter ruine of the Saints of God, and that not of a certaine number, but of all the godly without exception, for as the cruell Emperour <hi>Caligula wiſhed that all the Romans had but one head, that he might ſtrik it aff at one blow:</hi> So the deſire of the wicked is, that the Saints of God might periſh from the earth. The confederate Nations<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 83.4.</note> 
               <hi>will have Iſrael to be rooted out of memorie, that they be not a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Haman</hi> wil have all the <hi>Iews</hi> to periſh in one day: <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> and <hi>Iulian</hi> the apoſtate had a purpoſe to roote out the name of Chriſtians from under heaven. Laſtly their hatred is irreconciliable in reſpect of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, <hi>Cain</hi> will not be reconciled to his brother, albeit the Lord offer himſelfe to take up the matter.<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>Eſau</hi> layeth up in his heart the hatred of his brother, untill the death of his father. For this<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 27.4.</note> cauſe they are called not only enemies but likwiſe foes,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 27.2.</note> becauſe their enimitie is altogether implacable, and their ſeed, like that of <hi>Amalecke,</hi> is irreconciliable.</p>
            <p>Secondly, They are violent and cruel, in reſpect of their words, whereby ſometimes they expreſſe how they deſpiſe and contemne the Saints of God, as <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal</hi> ſpake of <hi>David.</hi> Sometimes they threaten to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute the extremity of their rage, and furie, as did <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacherib</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:58988:23"/>againſt <hi>Ezohia:</hi> and ſome-times they bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the Saints of God with calumnies, and reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as <hi>Shimei</hi> railed againſt <hi>David.</hi> In all which reſpects, they are ſaid,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 27.12.</note> 
               <hi>To ſpeake cruelly,</hi> and their words are compared<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 120.3.</note> 
               <hi>to a great ſcourge,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 58.3.</note> 
               <hi>and to ſharpe arrowes, to burning coales, and to the venome of Aſpes,</hi> for as any of theſe things can griveouſly hurt mans body: ſo the cruel words of violent men do great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grieve and afflict the hearts of the Saints of God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, They are called cruell and violent, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of action, and ſo their cruelty is beſt ſeen by ſome, and felt by others: for when they are permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Lord, to afflict his Saints, they expreſſe all manner of cruelty that can be deviſed, or executed, without regard of ſex, or age, or quality of perſons. Therefore it is that in holy Scripture they are called<note n="*" place="margin">2 Theſſa. 1.6</note> 
               <hi>Troublers, Oppreſsors,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 10.18.</note> 
               <hi>Perſecutors.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 15.20.</note> 
               <hi>Troublers,</hi> becauſe they ſuffer not the Saints of God to live in peace and quietneſſe, but frequently give them oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of griefe and ſorrow, under the ſenſe whereof they are forced to complaine to God.</p>
            <p>They are called <hi>Oppreſſors,</hi> by reaſon of the manifold injuries which they doe to the Saints of God, without any cauſe or occaſion: they do to others, what they would not be content ſhould be done to themſelves. And they are called <hi>Perſecutors,</hi> partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe though they finde not opportunity at the firſt to execute their malice, yet they diligently ſeek occaſion, and wait till they finde it, and partly becauſe they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the Saints of God, as ſavage beaſts doe ſet upon their prey, to which they are compared by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David</hi> in the 22. <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> Hiſtory telleth us, that <hi>Bajacet</hi> the fourth
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58988:24"/>king of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> by his countrey-men was called <hi>Gilderin,</hi> which ſignifieth lightning, becauſe in a great battell which his father <hi>Amorath</hi> fought againſt the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> he brake in with a part of the Army ſo fiercely and terribly, as if it had beene thunder and lightning. But there is a word in the <hi>Text,</hi> which is not to be lightly overpaſſed, ſeeing it includeth more than at firſt it would ſeeme to doe: For when the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of <hi>David</hi> are ſaid, <hi>To ſeeke afttr his ſoule,</hi> there are two things included.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">When the enemies of <hi>David</hi> ſeeke after his ſoule, there are two things includ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> That the harme which <hi>Davids</hi> enemies would doe to him, is not a light, but a grievous hurt. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, That they wiſh not only the death of <hi>Davids</hi> body, but likewiſe the deſtruction of his ſoule.</p>
            <p>Firſt I ſay, that the hurt and skaith which they wiſhed him, is not a light harme, which eaſily may be comported with, &amp; ſoon repared, but a great and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous hurt, which can neither be indured nor repared: This is not like other kindes of hurt, that ſometimes by men is done to men. King<note n="*" place="margin">1 Sam. 11.7</note> 
               <hi>Saul</hi> threatneth that the oxen of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſhall be cut in pieces, which follow him not to war againſt the <hi>Ammonits,</hi> &amp; cruel<note n="*" place="margin">1 Sam. 11.2</note> 
               <hi>Nahaſh will put out the right eyes of the Citizens of Iabeſh.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Luke 23.16</note> 
               <hi>Pontius Pilate will ſcourge Ieſus, and let him goe.</hi> But the enemies of <hi>David</hi> ſeeke after his ſoule, they wil not only ſpoil him of his wealth and honour, but likewiſe of his life: they are ſet againſt him, as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> were ſet againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Luke 23.21</note> 
               <hi>That will have him put to death.</hi> And as the <hi>Iewes</hi> were againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> when they ſaid,<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 22.22.</note> 
               <hi>It is not fit that he ſhould live.</hi> And as Hiſtory telleth, That <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Anjew,</hi> was ſo cruelly ſet againſt <hi>Conradine</hi> king of <hi>Cicily,</hi> that the proverbe vvent through the world, <hi>Vita Caroli
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58988:24"/>mors Conradini. The life of Charles was the death of Conradine, he ſhould not live except he died.</hi> And ſo the Scripture telleth us, That the life of <hi>David</hi> was fought by his enemies, both by ſecret plots, &amp; open violence, which not only maketh him to ſay,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 56.1.</note> 
               <hi>That his enemies would ſwallow him up,</hi> but likewiſe he compareth them to ſavage beaſts, which when they ſet upon a man, doe not ſimply byte him untill he bleed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther take they away one of his members, but they leave him not, untill he be dead, and have eaten their pleaſure of his carcaſe, wherefore he ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 27.2.</note> 
               <hi>That his enemies come upon him to eat up his fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, It importeth that the enemies of <hi>David</hi> not only deſired the death of his body, but likewiſe they wiſhed that his ſoule might periſh forever, the like example of matchleſſe cruelty, we ſhall hardly finde in prophane Hiſtory; for ſome-times we read of men that hath wiſhed the death of their enemies, and yet afterwards hath lamented their death. As it is ſaid of <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, that weeped over the dead body of <hi>Darius</hi> king of <hi>Perſia:</hi> Some-times though they lament not their death, yet they will cauſe them to be buried, as<note n="*" place="margin">2 Kings 9.34</note> 
               <hi>Iehu</hi> would have done to <hi>Iezabel:</hi> And as it is ſaid, that <hi>Hannibal</hi> the famous <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginian</hi> Captaine, cauſed the <hi>Romane Conſuls</hi> to be honourably buried, whom he had valiantly vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: ſome-times they will not ſuffer them to be buried, which was the deſpite that <hi>Caeſar</hi> uſed againſt the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of <hi>Pompei,</hi> who was vanquiſhed in the fields of <hi>Pharſaly.</hi> Albeit as one ſaid well,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Ignobilia ſunt odia qua ultra mortem procedunt. Barclaus. lib. <hi>4</hi> argendis.</note> 
               <hi>That is baſe hatred that goeth beyond death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Scripture telleth us of the baſe and barbarous deſpite of the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> that did open the graves of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58988:25"/>the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and ſcattered their bones upon the earth. The writters of the <hi>Indian</hi> Hiſtories relate, that many of theſe nations have a cuſtome to eat their enemies, which they take in the warre, and to make muſicall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of their bones. One example we read a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Pagans,</hi> who in his booke that he writeth againſt his enemie, whom he dar not name, he not only wiſheth many bodily miſeries to befall him, but likewiſe,<note n="(l)" place="margin">In loca ab eliſiis di verſa fugabere cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis quaſque tenent ſedes noxia turba coles. Et ibid nec mortis pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas mors alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra finiet hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius horaque erit tantis ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tima nulla malis. Ovid. in thin.</note> 
               <hi>That his ſoule may be tormented in hell with endleſſe paine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We read in the Goſpel that the <hi>Iewes</hi> thinke not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough <hi>that Chriſt ſhould die, unleſſe he be crucified, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſo they thought his ſoule ſhould periſh, by dieing a curſed death.</hi> But if it be asked how may it be known that this was the diſpight of <hi>Davids</hi> enemies, againſt him, I anſwere briefly in this plaine compariſon, if one man ſhall deſire another to goe from one place to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, in a way that he knoweth to be ful of robbers, and ſavage beaſts, out of all queſtion, he deſireth him to die: So the enemies of <hi>David</hi> did not only baniſh him from the houſe of God, where he was moſt deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to dwell, but likewiſe they bid him goe, and ſerve the gods of the Gentils, the 26. Chapter of the firſt of <hi>Samuel,</hi> that by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting idolatry he might periſh eternally: and therfore<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 86.13.</note> 
               <hi>he magnifieth the mercy of God, who in this reſpect delivered his ſoule from the loweſt hell.</hi> A two-fold uſe may be made of this point.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">The conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the cruelty of <hi>Davids</hi> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, teacheth us a two fold uſe.</note> Chriſtians ſhould have a ſingular care not only to look to their words and wayes, that they ſhow no ſignes of crueltie, but likewiſe that the ſpirit of crueltie be not harbured in their hearts, but rather that they may ſtudie to meekneſſe, and the exerciſe of mercie, and that for foure reaſons. Firſt, becauſe ſo we are
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58988:25"/>taught by the word of God.<note place="margin">We ſhould avoid crueltie and ſtudie to mercy for four reaſons.</note> Secondly becauſe cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie maketh men like Sathan: Thirdly in reſpect of our union with God. Fourtly, In reſpect of divine venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, which is the reward of crueltie.</p>
            <p>Firſt I ſay, becauſe Chriſtians are taught by the word of God, to flee crueltie, and follow mercie, and that by no leſſe example then God their Creator, and Chriſt their Redimer,<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 6.36.</note> 
               <hi>Be mercifull as your heavenly Father is mercifull</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 11.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>And learn of me that I am meek and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in heart:</hi> We juſtly thinke that both the Religion of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and the Religion of the <hi>Machometans,</hi> cannot be a good religion, ſeeing their religion teacheth them the practice of crueltie, and to force people with fire and ſword to imbrace it, whom they cannot perſwade by their arguments, even as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaketh of the carriage of the <hi>Arrians</hi> in his time, towards the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Chriſtians,</hi>
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">Quos non poſsunt ſermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus decipere, gladio cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant ferien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos, cruentas leges ore dict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, manu ſcribunt &amp; putant quod lex fidem ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perare poſsit Ambroſ lib. <hi>5</hi> epiſt <hi>32</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Whom they cannot deceive by word, they cry, that they are to be killed by the ſword, they indite cruell and bloudy lawes with their mouth, they write with their hand, and thinke that their lawes can command Faith unto men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Chriſtian and true Religion, which is ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the word of God, in this is known to be a good Religion, becauſe it injoyneth the hatred of crueltie and love of mercy, and will have none to be forced by violent compulſion, but rather perſwaded by power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full preaching, and evident arguments from divine truth, that men may acknowledge and imbrace the truth, according to the worthie ſaying of <hi>Tertulian,</hi>
               <note n="(n)" place="margin">Religionis non eſt cogere religionem, quae ſponte ſuſcipi debet, non vi, cum &amp; hoſtiae ab ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo libentiex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulentur. Tertu. lib. ad Scapulam.</note> 
               <hi>It is not the part of Religion to conſtraine Religion, which men ſhould willingly receive, and not by force, ſeeing the ſacrifices of the Lord are required of a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling minde:</hi> howbeit it cannot be denied but although
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58988:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:58988:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:58988:27"/>the Lord only can perſwade the heart: yet when the profeſſors of the truth have to doe with <hi>Heriticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> and prophane perſons, that live amongſt them, but walk not with them in the unitie of faith, and in the way of godlines refuſing to be informed, and hating to be reformed, ſuch may be conſtrained by humane Lawes, to uſe the meanes of the true Religion, that either their ſoules may be ſaved, or their impictie may be reſtrained, that it prove not ſcandalous to the people of God, and ſo the Scripture telleth us, that when <hi>Ioſias</hi> in the Reformation of the people of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> renewed the <hi>Covenant</hi> betwixt God and his people,<note n="*" place="margin">2 Chro. 34.32.</note> 
               <hi>He cauſed all Iudah and Benjamine to ſtand to it:</hi> albeit we have reaſon to thinke that many of them were affected to idolatrie in their hearts. But <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and all other enemies of the Truth, who thinke rather by rigorous perſecution, than by right imformation, to bring people to their erroneous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, thereby they declare to the world the cruelty and falſhood of their Religion.</p>
            <p>And therefore whoſoever is delighted with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of cruelty, and is averſe from the works of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, what ever profeſſion he make of the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he hath not found the converting power of the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſeeing, though<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 27.22.</note> 
               <hi>he hath the voice of Iacob,</hi> yet he hath the hands of <hi>Eſau,</hi> together with the cruell heart of <hi>Eſau.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe meek and merciful men are moſt like God, who glorieth in his mercy: ſo fierce and cruel men are moſt like Satan, who delights in cruelty, to whom is given the name of a deſtroyer in the 20. of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> becauſe he taketh pleaſure to deſtroy the creatures of God, ſo that when he cannot extend
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58988:27"/>his malice to men, he is content to exerciſe his cruelty on beaſts, as the Goſpel telleth us, of the legion of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils that drowned the <hi>Swine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Becauſe our happineſſe ſtandeth in an u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God, and the neernes of our acceſſe to God, augmenteth our bleſſedneſſe, according to the ſaying of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 65.4.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſsed is the man whom thou chooſeſt, and whom thou cauſeth to come to thee.</hi> Cruell men can have no ſociety nor fellowſhip with God:<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Who abhorreth the bloud-thirſtie,</hi> for amongſt all things that can be preſented to the minde or ſenſes of man, there is not any two things ſo contrary to another, as the mercifull Creator, and cruell creature.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe albeit cruel and malicious men for a time may get liberty to exerciſe their fury, yet in end they ſhal not eſcape the vengeance of God, which is the juſt reward of their cruelty. Amongſt the Pagans <hi>Hercules</hi> and <hi>Theſeus</hi> were famous, that ſubdued, and puniſhed cruell men, by whom many had beene injured and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed: And ſhall it not much more concerne the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Gods power &amp; juſtice, to render to cruel men the reward of their cruelty. It was obſerved by <hi>Plato</hi> the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi>
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">Nullus tam ſevere inimicum ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ulciſci po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt quam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſolet miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorum oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſores Plato in Timaeo.</note> 
               <hi>That there is no man upon earth, ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>virly can take vengeance on his enemie, as the Lord God uſeth to take vengeance on ſuch as oppreſſe poore men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This vengeance the Lord ſome time executeth by the hand of man which did make<note n="*" place="margin">Iudges 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>Adonibezek</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the juſtice of God, albeit it often falleth out, that men, whom God uſeth as inſtruments of his juſtice, looke not to the glory of God, but to ſacisfie their owne vindictive humour.<note n="*" place="margin">Iſai. 33.1.</note> 
               <hi>Woe to thee that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth, for when thou ſhalt ceaſe, another ſhall oppreſſe thee.</hi> The <hi>Meeds</hi> and the <hi>Perſians</hi> were no leſſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58988:28"/>cruell to the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> nor they had been to the people of God, but more frequently the Lord plagueth cruell men by his own immediate hand, with viſible judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the ſight of the world, to the glory of the power &amp; juſtice of God: We read in the hiſtory of the <hi>Macabees,</hi> that the bowels of the cruel <hi>Antiochus</hi> were tormented, who had cauſed the bowels of others to be tormented: and in the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> hiſtory, we read of the puniſhment of cruel <hi>Herod</hi> the great, for his cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as well againſt his owne Children, as againſt the Nobles, and people of the <hi>Iews.</hi> The Scripture like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe telleth us of the condigne puniſhment of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked<note n="*" place="margin">2 Chro, 21.8.</note> 
               <hi>Iehoram,</hi> king of <hi>Iudah.</hi> And in the ſea of hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, it is related of the cruel and bloudy <hi>Attila,</hi> king of the <hi>Huns,</hi> who was never moved with tears of any, to ſhew mercy or pitie, but as he delighted in the ſheding of humane bloud, while he lived, he was overtaken by the vengeance of divine juſtice in his greateſt triumph, in his mariage day, for he was chocked with his own bloud, which did flow abundantly from divers parts of his body, untill his wretched life was finiſhed. There are infinite examples both in Eccleſiaſtick hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, &amp; in the book of the <hi>Martyrs,</hi> of the juſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wherewith the cruell perſecutors of the Saintes of God in all ages have beene plagued: therefore it was worthily obſerved by <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
               <note n="(p)" place="margin">Certi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muset fiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res quod inul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manet quod perpetimur: quantoque mator fuerit perſecutionis iniuriatanto et iustior pro perſecutione viudicta. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preanus tract. coutra De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrium.</note> 
               <hi>We are ſure &amp; confident, that what we ſuffer ſhall not be unrevenged, and the greater the wrong of the perſecution be, ſomuch the more juſt and grievous ſhall be the revenge, which God ſhall take of the perſecutors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second uſe which here is to be obſerved, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever we heare of the cruelty of wicked men, againſt the Saints of God, in any place of the world, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:58988:28"/>when we our ſelves are threatned with their cruel ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility, then we ſhould put up our humble prayer to the Lord our God,<note place="margin">We ſhould pray to God to be delivered from cruell e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, for two reaſons.</note> that if he will chaſtiſe us for our ſins and offences, he would doe it with his own hand, and not give us * <hi>up to the will of our enemies:</hi> For <hi>David</hi> wiſely chooſed * <hi>to fall into the hand of God, rather than into the hand of men:</hi> Thus we ſhould pray: for two reaſons, Firſt, becauſe no favour towards the Saints can be expected at the hands of their perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors: Secondly, becauſe God, to whom the Saints pray, is both willing to heare, and able to helpe.</p>
            <p>Firſt I ſay, becauſe no favour, but extreme cruelty to the people of God, may be expected at the hands of the cruell enemies of God and his people, as <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> ſpeaketh of the king of <hi>Babylon,</hi> * <hi>which did ſhow no mercy to the people of the Iews.</hi> The Scripture com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth perſecution to a floud of water, for as a floud of water is not like an ordinary river, which runneth along in its owne channell, but altogether overflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth banke and brae, and violently carieth away what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it overtaketh: So perſecution is not like an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary war betwixt two Nations, that can give &amp; take reaſonable quarters, as occaſion is offered, but perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution paſſeth the bounds of Humanity, and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the bonds of Nature, and committeth outragious crueltie, that Humane ſenſe abhorreth, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting whereof maketh the eares to tingle, the fleſh to quake, and the heart to tremble,<note n="(q)" place="margin">Quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam animits meminiſſe horret luctu<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> refugit. Virg. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Aentid.</note> 
               <hi>So that the minde of man will abhorre the remembrance thereof with greife and ſorrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We need not to call to minde the antient examples of cruelty, that are regiſtrate in Eccleſiaſtick hiſtory, ſeeing of later times, we heard of the <hi>Spaniſh inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:58988:29"/>and that which hath beene uſed in the priſon houſes, and pillories of <hi>England,</hi> while as the tyranny of the <hi>Prelates</hi> advanced to that hight, that it could not ſtand: and that theſe yeares by-paſt, hath beene more than barbarouſly practiced by the <hi>Iriſh Rebels,</hi> againſt the Saints and ſervants of God. All this ſhould make us draw near to God, by humble prayer, that we be not expoſed to the cruelty of our enemies, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſeeing as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, * <hi>The very mercies of the wicked are cruell:</hi> For whatſoever favour cruell per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors offer to the people of God, is alwayes upon conditions, that are worſe than death. For as <hi>Wizards</hi> and <hi>Witches,</hi> when they cure mens bodies of diſeaſes, bring greater hurt to their ſoules, by the uſe of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull meanes, whereby they draw guilt upon their conſciences: and as that cruel <hi>Antiochus</hi> in the ſeventh chapter of the ſecond book of the <hi>Macabees,</hi> not only would have ſpared the mother, and her ſeven ſons, but likewiſe would have advanced them to wealth and honour, if they would have forſaken the Law of their God, and become idolaters: So the <hi>Malignant</hi> party will offer both peace, and preferment to the <hi>Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> that will break the <hi>Covenant,</hi> to which they have ſworne; and joyn with them in their unlawfull courſes, and wicked proceedings, that mirely tend to the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the true Religon, and erecting of idolatry and ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe our Lord to whom we pray is not like <hi>Baal,</hi> that neither could heare nor helpe his worſhippers, for our Lord is willing to heare, and able to help, and as be heareth us, when we pray, ſo he is able to grant our requeſts. For truly the caſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Saints of God were miſerable, if the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58988:29"/>might of their enemies were anſwerable to their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and their power to their purpoſes. But as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſaid to <hi>Pontius Pilate.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 19.11.</note> 
               <hi>They have no power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver God Saints but what is given them from above, the Lord firſt breaketh downe the hedge,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 80.12 13.</note> 
               <hi>And then the wild boare of the forreſt pilleth the bark of the vine that the Lord hath planted.</hi>
               <note n="(r)" place="margin">Impii non quando vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt ſanctis nocere poſſunt, ſed quando Deus illis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendi, tempus conceſserit, ut ſuis ſanctis. coronam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videat. Chry. Homil. <hi>25.</hi> ſupr. Ma.</note> It is a worthy ſaying of <hi>Chriſoſtome, wicked men cannot alwayes burt the Saints of God, when they pleaſe, but when the Lord granteth them a time to hurt them, that he may provide a crowne of glory for his Saints and ſervants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord that did ſend <hi>Senacherib</hi> to threaten <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekias,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 Kings 1.25.</note> 
               <hi>Who came not up without the Lord, did like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe put abridle in the lips of Senacherib, that hee was not able to hurt Ezekias, as he cruellie purpoſed:</hi> as then the proudeſt perſecutors without Gods permiſſion, are not able to trouble his Saints, ſo he can limit their power, and diſſapoint their purpoſes, and turne their rage to his praiſe, that his Saints that are preſerved from the furie of their enemies,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 124.8.</note> 
               <hi>may acknowledge their help to come from God, that made the heaven and the earth, and heartily bleſſe the Lord that hath not given them,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 124.6.</note> 
               <hi>to be a prey to their teeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now come we to the laſt particulare conſiderable in the enemies of <hi>David, who did not ſet God before them:</hi> this is to be under-ſtood in a three-fold reſpect: Firſt in reſpect of their different purpoſe from the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of God in troubling the Saints of God. Secondly becauſe they are not directed by the Light of God.<note place="margin">The perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of the Saints are ſaid not to ſet God before them in a three-fold reſpect.</note> Thirdly, becauſe they forget God, while as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider not his divine properties.</p>
            <p>Firſt I ſay, the proud enemies of <hi>David,</hi> and all the cruell perſecutors of Gods Saints ſet not God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58988:30"/>them, inreſpect of their different purpoſe, &amp; inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, from the purpoſe and intention of God while by Gods permiſſion they are inſtruments of the trouble of Gods Saints, for as in the crucifying of Chriſt, the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and intention of the <hi>Iews</hi> was to deſtroy him, but the purpoſe of God was, that Chriſt might be glorified, and his Elect redeemed. So when the Saints of God are perſecuted, the purpoſe and intention of God, is either that he may be glorified in the exerciſe and tryall of the faith and patience of his Saints: as in the 14. of the Revelation: or elſe that like a loving and wiſe father he may chaſtiſe his children by the rod of the wicked, for the ſins wherewith they have offended him, that they may repent, and turn to him, as we may read in the book of the Iudges in which reſpect <hi>Nebuchadne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> is called the ſervant of God: but the purpoſe of the perſecutors is either altogether to diſhonour God, and deſtroy his people, whereof Gods open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies make their boaſt in the 83. <hi>Pſalme:</hi> or elſe they doe carrie themſelves like ſome knaviſh ſervants, that worke their Maſters worke to their own advantage, and to their Maſters prejudice, as we may reade in the parable of the unjuſt ſteward the 16 of <hi>Lukes</hi> Goſpel for they altogether ſo reſpect themſelves by doing there own will, and ſeeking their own honour, that they have no regard at all to the pleaſing of God, or advancing of his honour. For while they perſecute the Saints of God, they care not how God be diſhonoured and diſpleaſed, providing they themſelves may be ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noured and well pleaſed by ſatisfying their wicked humours, and accompliſhing their cruell projects, and ſo they ſet not God before them, becauſe they ſerve not the Lord but themſelves,</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:58988:30"/>
            <p> Secondly, Becauſe though ſometime they thinke they are doing ſervice to God, yet they are not direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the light of God, but by a prepoſterous zeale,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 10.8.</note> which is without knowledge, they are like ſome fooliſh ſervants that while they think the work they are working will pleaſe their maſter, it greatly will of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him, and provocke him to anger. They are like <hi>Ioſua</hi> and his princes, that made covenant with the <hi>Gibionits,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 9.19.</note> 
               <hi>but asked not counſell of the Lord</hi> for our Saviour ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 16.2.</note> 
               <hi>That they that perſecute his Diſciples, ſhall think they doe ſervice to God,</hi> and he well ſaith, <hi>That it ſhall be according to their thinking, and not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to truth,</hi> for doubtleſſe they neither conſider aright whom they doe perſecute, nor for what they doe perſecute them, they conſider not that they doe perſecute God with his ſervants, <hi>Ananias</hi> ſaith to the Lord,<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 9.14.</note> 
               <hi>that Saul the perſecuter had a warrand from the high Prieſt to bind all that called upon the Name of the Lord,</hi> but Ieſus himſelf teſtifieth from heaven<note n="*" place="margin">2 Acts 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>That he was perſecuted whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Saints were perſecuted,</hi> neither conſider they for what they perſecute them, even for ſuch things as ſhould make them to love &amp; cheriſh, and reſpect them, for they perſecute them<note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse ſake, and for the Name of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Luke 6.22.</note> 
               <hi>and for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Truth</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Acts 24.14.</note> 
               <hi>which they call hereſie, and for walking in the way of godlineſse which they count ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and vanity,</hi> and therefore as our Saviour ſaith in the Goſpel:<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 11.9.</note> 
               <hi>He that, walketh in the day, ſtumbleth not becauſe he ſeeth the light of this world, but he that walketh in the night, ſtumbleth becauſe there is no light in him:</hi> ſo when a man is led by the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the light of God, he is convoyed ſafely and walketh ſecurely, but when hee is not led by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Gods light, it is no wonder though he miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carie,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58988:31"/>ſo fearfully, that he think that to be ſervice done to God, which is moſt offenſive to the Majeſtie of God, ſeeing they are not enlightned by the ſpirit of truth, but led by the light of miſ-informed conſcience, which is nor proper light, but darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>They ſet not God before them,</hi> becauſe they doe not remember God as they ought, they are of the number of the people,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 9.17.</note> 
               <hi>that forget God,</hi> ſeeing they do not conſider the preſence, nor the juſtice, nor the power of God, for other wiſe they durſt not perſecute nor oppreſſe his Saints, but rather would ſtrive to gaine their love and favour by profiting them to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of their power, ſeeing ſuch is the ſympathy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Chriſt and Chriſtians, that what evil or good is done to them, he thinketh it done to himſelfe, the 25 of <hi>Mathew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then, I ſay, they conſider not Gods all where preſence from whoſe ſight nothing can be hid, and in whoſe ſight all that men doe<note n="*" place="margin">Hab, 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>are naked and open.</hi> The light of nature teacheth man to know this which made on of the heathen to ſay<note n="(s)" place="margin">Eſt profecto Deus qui quae nos gerimus auditque &amp; videt. Plaut. in capteivis.</note> 
               <hi>Truly their is a God, who ſeeth, and heareth all that we doe.</hi> But all men make not a right uſe of this light, for ſuch is the groſſe athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme wherewith the hearts of the perſecutors of Gods Saints are repleniſhed, that they ſay with themſelves,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 10.11.</note> 
               <hi>God doeth not ſee them, neither will crave a reckoning of them,</hi> which either they think to be ſo, or indeed would have it ſo; but then their folly appeareth as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 94.4.</note> 
               <hi>Shall not he that made the eye ſee clearly</hi> even according to the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> rule,<note n="(t)" place="margin">Propter quod unu m<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quodque eſt tale id ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum eſt mains tale. Ariſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Topicon.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoever maketh a thing to be ſuch, it ſelfe moſt be more ſuch:</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can lurk fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſight who is the fountain &amp; Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſight, next they remember not the juſtice of God who certainly wil revenge, and cannot but revenge the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:58988:31"/>wrongs that are done to his ſervants,<note n="*" place="margin">2 Theſſ. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>It is a righteous thing with God to render tribulation to them that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, &amp; our Saviour telleth,<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 18.7.</note> 
               <hi>That the cryes of the Elect which night and day are ſend up to their heavenly father, ſhal quickly be avenged.</hi> Laſtly they conſider not the power of God, who is able to protect his weakeſt ſervants, &amp; to puniſh their ſtrongeſt enemies, he is not like <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> that for the ſtoning of his ſervant,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Kings 12.18</note> 
               <hi>is not able to puniſh the Iſraelits,</hi> but rather like <hi>David,</hi> who for the wrong done to his ſervants, did<note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 12.3.</note> grievouſly plague the <hi>Ammonits.</hi> And therefore both Scripture and Hiſtorie telleth us, that the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of Gods Saints, neither by their greatneſſe, nor multitude, could eſcape the avenging hand of the Lord, who is Almighty, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note n="(w)" place="margin">Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens eſt Deus faciendo quae Gult, non pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiendo quae non vuls. Aug. lib. <hi>5.</hi> decivitate dei.</note> 
               <hi>By doing what he willeth, not by ſuffering what he willeth not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The uſe of this point which Chriſtians ſhould make ſtandeth in this, their ſingulare care ſhould be both in the works of their Chriſtian &amp; particular calling<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 16.8. That a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian may ſet God before him, foure things are to be required.</note> 
               <hi>To ſet God alwayes before them.</hi> To which foure things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. Firſt that he look to the wil of God, as the rule of his actions. Secondly that he look to the glory of God, as the end of his actions. Thirdly, That he be led by the light of Gods word, and ſpirit. Fourtly that he remember God in his divine properties. Firſt I ſay, that they look to the wil of God as the rule of their actions,<note n="*" place="margin">Gala. 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>As many as follow this rule, mercy ſhall be on them, and peace,</hi> but this includeth two remarkable things.</p>
            <p>Firſt that a Chriſtian ſhould ſo look to Gods plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that he ſhould have no regard to mans pleaſure,<note place="margin">To looke to the will of God, as the rule of our actions, inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth two things.</note> that is to ſay, as he moſt not doe any thing offenſive to God, though thereby he ſhould pleaſe man, ſo he moſt not omit any thing that may pleaſe the Lord though by doeing thereof, he ſhould greatly offend
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:58988:32"/>man. There is a remarkable example in <hi>Eccleſiaſticke</hi> hiſtorie to this purpoſe, of the worthie Chriſtian <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the firſt, Emperour, who when by open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, he had forbidden the <hi>Egyptians</hi> to ſacrifice to the river <hi>Nilus,</hi> which had been their yearely cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome by their ſuperſtition, which had continued for many ages: it ſo fell out, that the next year after, that the river <hi>Nilus</hi> did not water the land of <hi>Egypt</hi> by ſuch abundance as it was wonte, for which when the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious people began to murmure, as though the reaſon thereof had beene the neglect of their wonted ſacrifice, the Governour wrot unto the Emperour, that he would look timouſly to the matter and conſider what might be the event, as if he would have deſired him to revock his former Edict, and to give way to the ſuperſtitious people to ſacrifice to <hi>Nilus,</hi> leſt they ſhould rebel. But the worthy Emperour anſwered him that he would not permit a thing to be done to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of God, for the pleaſure of men, &amp; he had rather that men ſhould be offended, before the Lord ſhould be diſpleaſed. It had beene good for <hi>Ioab</hi> if he<note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 11.21.</note> had ſo deeply conſidered the matter of <hi>Vriah,</hi> he had not offended God to pleaſe his king, it was better conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> who willed the <hi>Iews</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Acts 5.29.</note> 
               <hi>to judge whither it were better to obey God, than men.</hi> For ſeeing none can ſerve two Maſters, it is the beſt and wiſeſt courſe to ſerve the beſt and worthieſt Maiſter, according to the ſaying of <hi>Gregorie,</hi>
               <note n="(x)" place="margin">Quomodo ergo a vobis poteſt par ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerberi famu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latus quorum dipar eſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatus Greg. bomil. <hi>12.</hi> in Evang.</note> 
               <hi>How can it be required of you that ye all ſhould give a like ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to Maſters that are of an unlike name,</hi> That is to ſay, Mortall men, and the eternall God.</p>
            <p>It were good that this were deeply laid to heart by many Malignants, that trouble the peace of the Saints of God, that they might look more to the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58988:32"/>of their heavenly, then their earthly king, for ſo ſhould they doe more acceptable ſervice to God and more profitable ſervice to their king.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It includeth that he that doeth the will of God, and maketh it the rule of his actions, ſhould not be deſirous to conforme Gods will to his will, but rather to ſtudie to conforme his will to Gods wil. For if this ſhould be the carriage of ſervants towards their earthly Maſters, much more ought it ſo to be towards God, their heavenly Maſter: whom <hi>Auguſtine</hi> bringeth in thus ſpeaking,<note n="(y)" place="margin">Ille meus miniſter eris qui non audire quod voluerit para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt, ſed vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le quod audie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Auguſt. in Pſal. <hi>118.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He ſhal be my ſervant, who is ready no to heare what he willeth, but to will what he heareth.</hi> Which a Chriſtian muſt carefully look to, not only in the abſtaining from things that ought to be avoyded, but likewiſe in doing things, that ought to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the one, becauſe they are forbiden, the other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are commanded of the Lord, for thereby a Chriſtian giveth teſtimony of his ſincer obedience in the ſight of God, according to the ſaying of <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>
               <note n="(z)" place="margin">Verus obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diens non at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendit quale pracipitur, ſed hoc contentus eſt quia prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipi tur. Aug. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>He that is truly obedient, doth not conſider what ſort of thing is commanded, but with this he is only content that it is commanded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, That a Chriſtian may ſet God before him, it is not only required that he look to the will of God, as the rule, but likewiſe that he looke to the glory of God as the end of his actions, for in this is the fidelitie and ſincerity of the ſervants of God mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted who ſhall obtaine their Maſters approbation in the day of their reckoning for then a Chriſtian may be ſaid, to look to the glory of God, as the end of his actions, when he ſo zealouſly tendereth the bonour of God, that he will not doe any thing to diſhonour him though thereby he ſhould make never ſo much profit and commoditie, neither will hee omit any thing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58988:33"/>whereby God ſhould bee honoured, though by doing of it, he ſhould incurre both skaith and ignominy. We reade of the ſervants in the parable of the <hi>talents,</hi> that they ſo reſpected their Maſters honour, that they rendered into his hands both the talents they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and thoſe they had gained, committing the diſtribution of their rewards to their Maſters diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Happie is that Chriſtian, that can ſay with Chriſt<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 17.4.</note> that in finiſhing the work which God hath given him to doe, he hath glorified God upon earth, for he may be well aſſured,<note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 2.30</note> 
               <hi>that as they that diſhonour God, ſhal come to ſhame, ſo they that honour him ſhall be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured of him.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 12.26.</note> 
               <hi>If any man ſerve me him ſhall my father honour, ſaith our Saviour</hi> in the Goſpel; upon which words <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Sic mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrantem Chriſto hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rificabit pater cius honore illo magno ut ſit cum filio cius nec unqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deficiet faelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas eius. Aug. tract. <hi>51.</hi> in Ioan.</note> 
               <hi>So ſhall the Father of Chriſt honour the ſervant of Chriſt, with that great honour, that he may be with his Sonne, neither ſhall his happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe at any ty me faile or fall away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. He that ſetteth God before him, muſt be led by the light of his word, &amp; ſpirit, for the word of God,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> 
               <hi>Is a light to our feet, &amp; a la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tern to our paths.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Luke 1.79.</note> 
               <hi>It giveth light to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſit in darknes, &amp; in the ſhadow of death.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal 27.19.</note> 
               <hi>The prophet David intreateth the Lord,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>To teach him his wayes, &amp; to lead him in a right path, becauſe of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi> The Scripture telleth us,<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 16.13.</note> 
               <hi>That the holy Spirit is the unction, that teacheth us all things, * And leadeth us in all truth,</hi> which is not to be underſtood of extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinar, but ordinar revelations when he maketh us to underſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the true meaning of the writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> word of God, that we may flee the evil, which is to be avoyded, &amp; follow the good which is injoyned and commanded.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, He that ſetteth God before him, muſt remember God in the fore-named properties, in his ubiquity, juſtice, and power: he muſt conſider that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:58988:33"/>God is all where preſent, to take notice both of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and outward converſation of men whither it be good or evil. Therefore <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Deustotus oculus eſt quia omnia videt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus totus eſt quia om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia operatur totuspes eſt quia ubique est. Aug in Pſal. <hi>120.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That God is all an eye, which ſeeth all things, all hand, who work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all things, and all foot, who walketh every where.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He muſt likewiſe remember, that the righteous Lord wil neither ſuffer the evil doing of men to be unpuniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor their good doings unrewarded, of the one, the Church ſaith in the booke of the <hi>Lamentations,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Lament. 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is righteous, for I have rebelled:</hi> And of the other the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 6 10.</note> 
               <hi>God is not unjuſt, to forget your work &amp; labour of love.</hi> Laſtly, he muſtremember the power of the Almighty God,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 135.6.</note> 
               <hi>Whereby he doth whatſoever he wileth in heaven, and earth.</hi> And can do all that he can will, without impediment: according to the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Tertulian,</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Deipoſſe velle eſt, &amp; non poſſe nolle eſt. Tertul. in apologe.</note> 
               <hi>To be able with God, is to will, and not to be able, is not to will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereby likewiſe he can puniſh ſinners for their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity notwithſtandſting of their greatnes amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt men, &amp; the multitude wherwith they combine in the courſe of ſin, by which power likewiſe,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 91.1.</note> 
               <hi>He protecteth his Saints in their greateſt danger and difficulty, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth &amp; ſtrengthneth them,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Colo. 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>in their greateſt trouble and calamity,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Epheſ. 3.20.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; ſatisfieth their deſire exceeding abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly.</hi> Now there are three reaſons wherfore a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſhould carefully labour thus to ſet God before him: Firſt,<note place="margin">There are three reaſons wherefore a Chriſtian ſhould always ſet God before him.</note> becauſe amongſt many other differences this is one moſt remarkeable betwixt the Elect and the Reprobate; betwixt men in the ſtate of nature, and in the ſtate of grace. Spirituall men like <hi>David,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal 16.8.</note> 
               <hi>ſet God alwayes before them,</hi> but wicked and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, like the enemies of <hi>David,</hi> doe not at all ſet God before them: but live in the world<note n="*" place="margin">Epheſ. 2.12</note> 
               <hi>without hope, and without God,</hi> and by their carriage, declare to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58988:34"/>the world,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal 36.1.</note> 
               <hi>That they are void of the feare of God,</hi> but when Chriſtians ſet God before them, this is an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent note of their effectuall calling,<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 26.16.</note> 
               <hi>Whereby they are turned from the power of Satan unto God,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Coloſ. 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>And tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the power of darkneſſe unto the Kingdome of the Son of God.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>And are called out of darkneſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the marveilous light of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If we conſider the happines of ſuch as ſet God before them, and the miſery of thoſe that ſet not God before them, the happineſſe of the one appeareth in this, that as they ſet God before them, ſo he ſetteth them before him: For in all reciprocall offices betwixt God and man, that is in thoſe things which are mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally done by God to man, and by man to God, the Lord is alwayes the preveener, and beginner, ſo that a man by the performance of his part, may certainly know that God performeth his. There is mutuall love betwixt God and his Saints, but God firſt beginneth, as the <hi>Apoſtle Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>And they that love God,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 8.17.</note> 
               <hi>may know that they are beloved of God</hi> God hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen that man for his portion,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 73.25.</note> 
               <hi>who chooſeth God for his portion.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 119. ult.</note> 
               <hi>And God ſeeketh us, before we can ſeek him,</hi> and whoſoever ſet God before them, by doing his will, and ſeeking his honour, by following his light, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring his properties, the Lord ſetteth them before him by a high eſtimation of them, by tender &amp; earneſt love towards them, and by a fatherly &amp; provident care about them.<note n="*" place="margin">Eſai. 49.16.</note> 
               <hi>I have graven thee upon the palmes of my hands, and thy wals are continually before me.</hi> But the miſerie of the other is anſwerably great, for it may be ſaid of them, as the <hi>Latine Comicke</hi> faith of harlots,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Nec pol iſtae metuunt Deos, neque has reſpicere D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os opinor. Terent in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyra actu <hi>5.</hi> Scenae <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That they fear not God, and God regardeth them not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For as they have no purpoſe to advance Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſo God hath no purpoſe of their ſafety, and as they
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58988:34"/>will not hear God, when he cals on them in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity,<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 1 24.</note> 
               <hi>ſo he wil not hear them when they call on him in their adverſitie,</hi> &amp; as they contravine Gods reveil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led wil, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they lived upon earth, ſo he croſſeth their wil, when they are tormented in hell, which they teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie by gnaſhing of their teeth, which maketh <hi>Bernard</hi> to ſay,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Fruſtra volent quod nunquam erìt, &amp; ſruſtra no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent quod ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per erit. Bern. ſerm. <hi>10</hi> in Pſal. <hi>90.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That in vaine they ſhal wil, which never ſhal be, and in vaine they ſhall nill, which ever ſhall be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in a word as they were careleſſe to walke as in his preſence,<note n="*" place="margin">2 Theſſ 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>So they ſhall be for ever baniſhed from the preſence of God, and glorie of his power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, This is required in reſpect of our ſpirituall walking, <hi>For</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtians muſt not walke like the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils, which knew not God,</hi> but rather like<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 1.6</note> 
               <hi>Zacharie, and Elizabeth</hi> in all the commandments of God,<note n="*" place="margin">Coloſ. 1.10</note> 
               <hi>This is called a walking worthy of the Lord,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Gala. 5.25</note> 
               <hi>a walking in the ſpirit,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 8.1.</note> 
               <hi>and after the ſpirit, a walking with God, as did Enoch,</hi> and before God, as<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 5.25</note> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> was injoyned. Now there is no poſſibility that any can ſo walke,<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 17.1</note> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe hee ſet God before him, for this indeed ſhall make him know the way wherein, the manner how, and the end towards which he ought to walke, that in all theſe reſpects he may make conſcience of his walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſight of God, by <hi>walking in his command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with a perfect heart,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 84.7.</note> 
               <hi>from strength to ſtrength, towards Sion, where he ſhall ſee the Lord of Loſts,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Coloſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>and by walking worthily of the Lord, pleaſing h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>th all things, he may be fruitfull in good workes, and increaſe in the knowledge of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which heavenly, and holy diſpoſition, God of his infinite mercy bring all our ſoules, for the ſake of Jeſus. <hi>To whom with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt, be all praiſe, honour, and glory, world without end, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
